So feel free to get started, whenever you want to be ready.
只要你想做好准备，就可以开始了。
Alright, should we start then.
好的，那我们开始吧。
Please.
请。
Alright, hey everyone, my name is Felipe,
好了，大家好，我是 Felipe ，
I'm working with Caralina
我和 Caralina 一起工作，
and today we're going to be presenting on our project on distributed private electronic voting.
今天，我们将介绍
So motivating this project was you know actually sort of sort of easy,
所以这个项目的动机其实很简单，
given the current events and elections that had to happen with [covert] restrictions,
给出当前的事件和选举，
so we ask the question how would Internet voting work.
所以，我们提出了这个问题，
And, we're we're focusing specifically on maintaining voter privacy,
我们特别关注维护选民隐私，
or you know keeping votes private,
或者让投票保密。
and so here's a sketch of how a voting system might work.
以下是投票系统的工作原理，
You have a bunch of voters,
你有一些选民，
in this case, you know five
在这种情况下，有五个，
and then a vote counter,
然后是一个计票器，
the voters send their votes to the vote counter,
选民把他们的选票送到机票器，
and the vote counter is
而计票器是，
you know maybe they send them encrypted or some sort of security,
也许他们会加密发送，或者某种安全措施，
the vote counter decrypts them,
机票器解密它们，
make sure that each voter votes at most once
确保每个选民最多投票一次，
and computes a winner.
并计算出获胜者。
And so you know key thing to notice here is that,
所以这里要注意的关键是，
in order for the vote counter to determine that every voter vote [] at most once,
为了使计票器确定每个选民最多投一次票，
each vote has to be in some way linked to the voter,
每一张选票都必须以某种方式与选民联系在一起，
which which is dangerous,
这很危险。
so we're going to explain our threat model here.
我们将在这里解释我们的威胁模型，
Which is we're giving the attacker two sort of capacity
也就是我们给了攻击者两种能力，
or two two sort of powers,
或者两种力量，
the first is to create fell stop failures,
第一种是制造崩溃停止失败，
but not byzantine failures,
但不是拜占庭式的失败，
so the attacker can crash server,
这样攻击者就可以使服务器崩溃，
but it cannot sort of make it misbehave.
但它不能让它行为不端。
And you know whether there is a reasonable assumption is a question for another day,
这是否有一个合理的假设是另一个问题，
but we think there are other protocols that deal with this issues,
但我们认为还有其他协议可以处理这个问题，
we're not dealing with byzantine failures.
我们不是在处理拜占庭式的失败。
The the second power we give them is
我们给他们的第二种力量是，
to passively spy on a on a vote counter
监视计票器上的人，
and so this is problematic,
所以这是有问题的，
because as we said votes are linked with their voters
因为正如我们所说，选票与他们的选民是联系在一起的，
and so a passive attacker,
所以，一个被动的攻击者，
that's spying on the server, can sort of deanonymized those votes.
对服务器的间谍活动，
And so here's where we come in
这就是我们的用武之地，
and present our distributed voting design,
并展示我们的分布式投票设计，
we're going to deal with the first problem,
我们要处理第一个问题，
which is you know the [adviser] crashing the servers,
也就是对手使服务器崩溃，
and so we are going to have several vote counters,
我们将有几个投票器，
and the idea is that,
我们的想法是，
each voter will send other votes to all the vote counters,
每个投票者都会把其他选票送到所有的投票器，
and the vote counters will use the same protocols before and compute winners,
而计票器将使用与之前相同的协议
[other] winners, sorry,
[]获胜者，抱歉，
and it's this is good,
这很好，
because you add a second crash,
因为再加上一个崩溃，
sort of like n-1 vote counters
比如 n-1 个计票器，
as long as one of them is up and running,
只要其中一个还在运行，
we will be able to compute a winner.
我们就能够计算出获胜者。
However it's very you know arguably more unsafe for the second type of attack,
然而，这是非常不安全的，
which was passively [fine],
这是被动的[很好]，
because as long as you know as as a adversary,
因为作为一个对手，
the attacker can compromise, even one server,
攻击者甚至可以危害一台服务器，
you know it can deanonymized votes,
它可以取消匿名投票，
so that's where we're introducing Shamir Secret Sharing,
这就是我们要介绍 Shamir 秘密共享，
for Shamir sharing, we have a voter,
对于 Shamir 秘密共享，我们有一个投票器，
that's gonna, you know choose a vote either 0 or 1,
这将是，选择一个投票 0 或 1 ，
and we're gonna, you know I'm not going to explain how Shamir actually works,
我们会，
it's a cryptographic protocol,
它是一种加密协议，
but we're gonna just you know show what it allows us to do,
但我们要展示它允许我们做什么，
you pass vote through Shamir, where you give it two parameters, n and k,
你通过 Shamir 传递投票，
and it's going to create n part,
它将产生 n 个部分，
which allow you to re-compute that vote,
允许你重新计算选票，
the n parts could completely random,
这 n 个部分可以完全随机，
and in fact, what is sort of powerful,
事实上，最强大的是，
but Shamir is even k-1 shares give you no information about the original vote,
但是 Shamir 即使是 k-1 个部分
but given k or more shares,
但如果有 k 或更多的部分，
you can use Shamir to re-compute that vote.
你可以使用 Shamir 重新计算那个选票。
So we're going to show Shamir voting scheme.
所以，我们将展示 Shamir 投票方案。
so, yeah, now for the Shamir voting voting scheme,
所以，现在，对于 Shamir 投票方案，
so first all the voters are going to choose their vote
首先，所有的选民要选择他们的选票，
and share parts of the vote counters
并共享部分计票器，
and the complete vote on the different parts
以及对不同部分的完整投票，
and so the both counters are going to receive the parts
两个计票器都将接收部分，
and when they have the parts of all the voters,
当它们得到所有选民的部分时，
they're going to some these parts
它们将这些部分相加，
and share the sum with the vote counters,
并将 SUM 分享给机票器，
so here it's important to note that,
所以这里需要注意的是，
this summit looks like completely at random
这个 SUM 看起来完全是随机的，
and so by sharing it with the both counters,
所以，通过与两个计数器共享它，
the other both counters, they cannot learn anything about the parts that a received,
其他两个计票器，
so, this, ensures that the privacy of the voters is maintained,
所以，这保证了选民的隐私得到维护，
so they exchange their votes
所以他们交换了他们的选票，
and when a vote counter has received case sums
当机票器收到 SUM 时，
from other voters are including their part,
来自其他选民的包括他们的一部分，
they can finally compute the winner,
他们最终可以计算出获胜者，
so using a Shamir secret sharing again, black box,
所以再次使用 Shamir 秘密共享，黑色盒子，
it will like a re-compute the sum
它会像重新计算 sum ，
and if we get something that is greater than half of the number of voters, than the winner is 1,
如果我们得到的选票超过选民总数的一半，
and if it is less than, the winner would be 0,
如果小于，则获胜者是 0 ，
and yes so we finally have a winner.
是的，我们最终有了获胜者。
Now, some of the assumptions of our scheme are
现在，我们方案的一些假设是，
first that the voters and vote counters are well behaved
首先，选民和计票器都表现良好，
and follow the protocol or their parts some to what they say sounds like good intentions
并遵循协议，
and we only handle fail stop failures with this scheme,
我们使用这个方案只处理故障停止失败。
so yeah now to handle some of the scenarios,
所以，现在来处理一些情况，
first if we have an unreliable network scenario,
首先，如果我们有一个不可靠的网络方案，
all of the RPCs that we send in our servers are going to be sent periodically
我们在服务器中发送的所有 RPC 都将定期发送，
until we receive an acknowledgement that it has been received,
直到我们收到它已被接收的确认，
then to handle both failures,
然后为了处理选民失败，
so we we need to persist all of the voters,
所以我们需要持久化所有选民，
like persist the parts they computed and their vote,
比如持久化他们计算的部分和他们的投票，
because if we re-compute parts,
因为如果我们重新计算部分，
and then the vote counters had different parts,
然后计票器有不同的部分，
then the correctness of the scheme will be gone
那么方案的正确性就会消失，
and they would not be able to correct the sum,
他们将不能修正 sum ，
so it's important to always share like parts from the same computation
所以，重要的是始终共享来自同一计算的部分，
and not like change parts
而不修改部分，
and finally to handle the vote counter failures,
最后，为了处理计票器失败，
here we rely on Shamir secret sharing scheme
这里我们依赖于 Shamir 秘密共享方案，
and so as we mentioned before,
正如我们之前提到的，
we only need k servers to compute the winner,
我们只需要 k 个服务器来计算获胜者，
so, the system is referring to n-k crashes of vote counters.
所以，系统[] n-k 个计票器崩溃。
And now it is demo time,
现在是演示时间，
so I'll stop sharing screen and share another screen.
所以，我停止共享屏幕，并共享另一个屏幕。
And so here is our demo,
这是我们的 demo ，
basically we have 5 voters here,
我们这里有 5 名选民，
so we have 3 vote counters, 5 voters
我们有 3 个投票器，5个投票者，
and k is equal to 2,
而且 k 等于 2 ，
this means that network is unreliable,
这意味着网络是不可靠的，
and now if we run it,
现在如果我们运行它，
here, so we got 3
在这里，我们有 3 个，
and we get the winner is 1,
我们得到的获胜者是 1 ，
we can also crash one of the servers,
我们也可以让其中一台服务器崩溃，
since k is equal to 2,
因为 k 等于 2 ，
we can still compute a winner by having only two servers up,
我们仍然可以通过只有两台服务器运行来计算获胜者，
and so now if we run it,
所以现在如果我们运行它，
we get the winner of the election is say one again,
我们得到的选举获胜者还是 1 ，
and this is the end of our presentation,
我们的展示到此结束，
thank you very much for listening
非常感谢你的收听，
and we'll take some questions.
我们将回答一些问题。
Feel free to ask questions.
请随意提问。
Curious, how extensively you tested this system,
好奇的是，你测试这个系统的范围有多广，
like do you have a try in much different other configurations,
比如，你有没有尝试过不同的其他配置，
do you have performance numbers?
你们有性能数字吗？
Sure, so, we we did have like different sizes of,
当然，我们确实有不同大小的，
we create a whole test suite
我们创建了一整套测试套件，
and make sure to test like voter failures, server failures have different sizes
确保测试投票者故障，服务器故障有不同的大小，
and we don't have performance numbers,
我们没有性能数据，
we didn't test that,
我们没有测试过，
but in terms of like failures
但就失败而言，
and and different like numbers of voters vote counters,
以及不同数量的投票者，投票器，
yeah we have a full test suite
是的，我们有一套完整的测试套件，
and that we should have put the link and get for github,
我们应该把链接放到 github 上，
but we can you know send it to you, if you, you want,
但是我们可以把它发给你，如果你想要的话，
so you can check like look over implementation, under testing.
你可以在测试中检查查看实现。
There, more questions?
好的，还有问题吗？
Can you say something maybe a little bit like what ideas from 6.824
你能说点比如 6.824 的想法吗，
were you able to apply in the in this system,
你在这个系统里应用的，
other than using the testing framework.
而不是使用测试框架。
Sure, kind of do you want to take this one or should I take?
当然， Caro 你想要说这个，还是我来？
Sure, I'm, so here,
当然，所以在这里，
I guess, yeah this game actually comes from a pizza from the cryptography class
我想，这个游戏来自
and so it was fun to look at it from a different perspective,
所以，从不同的角度来看它是很有趣的，
so now we're not like focusing that much on the security,
现在我们关注安全问题，
I need but more like what happens if the individual like servers,
我需要，如果个别的服务器会发生什么，
if they fail,
如果它们失败了，
so both handling voter failures, handling vote counter failures, problems with the network,
无论是处理投票者故障、处理投票器故障，
I guess we didn't address specific partitions,
我想我们没有解决分区问题，
because it would work similar to both counter crushed,
因为它的工作原理类似于投票器，
Yeah, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Yeah, you have something to say.
除非你有话要说，
We're out of time a bit, so,
我们有点超时了，所以，
yeah, cool awesome, nice job, thanks for sharing.
好的，酷，干得好，谢谢分享。
Okay, we have a presentation on private analytics.
好的，我们有一个关于私有分析的演讲。
If Kevin is ready to share, awesome,
如果 Kevin 准备好分享，太棒了，
take it away, I'll be ready.
请开始，我会准备好的。
Okay, you guys can hear me and you guys can see my pointer?
好的，你们能听到我的声音吗，你们能看到我的鼠标吗？
Yes.
是的。
Okay, cool,
好的，酷，
everyone, I'm Kevin
各位好，我是 Kevin ，
and today I'm going to be presenting this very creatively named system called Sys,
今天，我将介绍这个非常有创意的命名为 Sys 的系统，
and this is a system for collecting aggregate statistics in a privacy preserving way,
这是一种以保护隐私的方式收集汇总统计数据的系统，
and so the last presentation was good leading to my project,
所以上一个演示很好地引导了我的项目，
so for the most part in 6.824,
在 6.824 的大部分时间里，
we've talked about how we can build reliable systems in the presence of byzantine or [] fails,
我们已经讨论了，
so servers can crash
所以服务器可能会崩溃，
and clients are generally well behaved,
客户端通常都表现得很好，
but from this talk,
但从这次演讲来看，
I hope you learn some new concepts
我希望你能学到一些新概念，
on how we can build systems with strong guarantees in the presence of byzantine failures
关于我们如何在出现拜占庭式故障的情况下建立具有强大保障的系统，
on behalf of both clients and servers within the system.
代表系统内的客户端和服务器。
And the main tools that we're going to use to achieve these guarantees are cryptographic primitives,
我们要使用的主要工具
such as multiparty computation and zero-knowledge proofs
例如多方计算和零知识证明，
and also distributed computing primitives, such as broadcast.
以及广播之类的分布式计算原语，比如广播。
Okay, so for simplicity,
好的，为了简单起见，
let's say we just want to build a system that computes sums,
假设我们想建立一个计算和的系统，
so we're going to have an aggregation server,
所以，我们将拥有一个聚合服务器，
that stores key value store,
存储键值存储，
so the keys are going to be indices for some statistics
键将成为某些统计数据的索引，
and the values are going to be tuples of sums,
值将是和的元组，
and we're gonna have a bunch of clients,
我们会有一堆客户端，
so each client is gonna have some identity,
所以每个客户端都会有一些身份，
say its client IP addresses,
比如它的客户端 IP 地址，
it's going to have the index of the statistic they wanna bump
它会有他们想要增加的统计数据的索引，
and it's also going to have its private inputs,
而且它也将有它的私有输入，
so the most straightforward thing to do is,
所以最直接的做法就是，
we can have all the clients send their inputs to the server as is
我们可以让所有客户端按原样将其输入发送到服务器，
and they can compete the sums,
它们可以计算和，
but obviously this is bad,
但显然这很糟糕，
because now this leads everything, right,
因为现在这引领了一切，
the server will learn the client's identity,
服务器将获知客户端的身份，
it'll learn the index being bumped
它将获得发出的索引，
and they'll learn their private input.
它将获得它们的私有输入。
So we can do a little bit better,
所以我们可以做得更好一点，
we can compute these sums privately,
我们可以私下计算这些和，
if we deploy to non colluding servers,
如果我们部署到非合谋服务器，
and then we're going to have each client secret share their input to each of these servers,
然后，我们将让每个客户端
so as we said in the previous presentation,
正如我们在上一次演示中所说的，
so each server, each signature alone leaks no information about the client's private input,
每个服务器、每个签名本身都不会泄露有关客户端私有输入的信息，
but still the servers can add up these shares
但服务器仍然可以将这些份额相加，
and compute a local version of the key value store,
并计算出一个键值存储的本地版本，
and then later when the servers want to recover the actual sums,
然后稍后当服务器想要恢复实际和时，
they can combine their local key value stores
它们可以合并它们本地的键值存储
to reconstruct the global key value store,
重建全局键值存储，
and this is a little bit better,
这个好了一点，
at least if one of these servers is honest,
至少如果这些服务器中有一个是诚实的，
then the servers are still gonna learn the client's identity,
那么服务器仍然会获知客户的身份，
they're still going to learn the client's index,
它们仍将获取客户的索引，
but now instead of learning each individual client's input,
但现在不是获得每个客户端的输入，
they're going to learn the sums of all clients and inputs,
它们将获得所有客户端的和和输入，
okay, so that's better,
好的，这样好多了，
but still a problem,
但这仍然是个问题，
namely that this identity index relation can still leak a lot of information.
也就是，这个身份索引关系仍然可以泄露大量信息。
So how can we fix this,
那么我们如何才能解决这个问题，
we can make things anonymous,
我们可以让事情匿名，
so we're still going to adapt setup from the [floor],
所以，我们仍将调整[]的设置，
but now we're going to give each server a public key for encryption,
现在我们给每台服务器提供一个公钥用于加密，
and that each client is going to encrypt each of their shares,
并且每个客户端都将对其每个份额进行加密，
and instead of having the clients send their shares directly to servers,
并且不是让客户端将它们的份额直接发送到服务器，
now we're going to have a layer of forwarding proxies in between,
现在，我们将在两者之间设置一层转发代理，
and so what's going to happen is,
所以接下来会发生的是，
the clients going to send their encrypted shares via broadcast to those proxies
客户端将通过广播将其加密的共享发送到这些代理，
and the proxies will route each share to their respective servers,
并且代理将每个共享发送到它们各自的服务器，
and then the aggregation can go as as explained,
然后聚合可以像解释的那样进行，
and so what are the privacy guarantees here,
那么，这里的隐私保障是什么，
if at least one of these properties is honest,
如果这些[财产]中至少有一个是诚实的，
then the proxy will still learn the client's identity
代理仍将获知客户端的身份，
and it'll learn some timing information,
它会获得一些计时信息，
based on when the client set the share,
基于客户端何时设置共享，
but nothing else,
但没别的了，
because the shares are encrypted to the server,
因为共享被加密到服务器，
so they learn nothing from that,
所以它们没有从中获得任何东西，
and then if at least one of the servers is honest,
如果这些服务器中至少有一个是诚实的，
then the servers will also learn some timing information based on the proxy forward it,
服务器也会获得一些计时信息，
it will certainly learn the index of the statistic
它还会获得统计的指标，
and learn the sum,
并获得和，
but most importantly as long as not both proxy and server are compromised at the same time,
但最重要的是，
then this design unlinks the identity from the index being bumped,
然后，这个设计将身份与被导出的索引解除链接，
which is exactly what we wanted, right,
这正是我们想要的，
so this is great,
所以这很棒，
but this also leads to another problem,
但这也导致了另一个问题，
namely that now clients can hide behind the privacy
也就是说，现在客户端可以躲在隐私后面，
and anonymity guarantees of the system to send bad inputs, right,
以及匿名保证系统发送错误的输入。
so let's say the system expected client inputs to be zeros and ones,
假设系统预期客户端输入为 0 和 1 ，
well behind this [] of privacy,
在这种隐私的后面，
now the client can send the secret share of a billion through the system,
现在客户端可以通过系统发送 10 亿的签名，
and now it can undetectably skew this sum,
现在它可以在无法察觉的情况下扭曲这个和，
so clearly this is bad.
所以，很明显，这很糟糕。
Let's fix this,
我们来解决这件事，
we want to make the system more robust,
我们想让这个系统更强大，
so what we're going to do is,
所以我们要做的是，
we're going to have each client generate,
我们将让每个客户生成，
what's called a zero-knowledge proof over their shares
所谓的对它们分享的零知识证明，
and send these to the servers,
并将这些发送到服务器，
and the many servers collect these zero-knowledge proofs,
许多服务器收集这些零知识证明，
they can interactively check that the client's inputs,
它们可以交互地检查客户端的输入，
actually the client shares actually reconstruct to some well formed input,
实际上，客户端共享重建为一些格式良好的输入，
and because this proof is in zero-knowledge,
因为这个证明是零知识的，
it leaves nothing about input, other than that it's well formed,
它没有留下任何关于输入的内容，
and so again our privacy properties stay the same,
所以我们的隐私属性又一次保持不变，
the property still learns that client's identity,
代理仍会获得客户端的身份，
is still learns some timing information,
仍能获得一些定时信息，
the server learns timing information,
服务器获知定时信息，
it learns the index and learns the sums,
它获得索引和获得和，
but now we've protected the system against malicious clients,
但现在我们已经保护系统不受恶意客户端的攻击，
because it'll only accept well formed inputs,
因为它只接受格式良好的输入，
and so this is great,
所以这很棒，
still there's another problem,
还有另一个问题，
which is that servers can crash
就是服务器可能会崩溃，
and we can lose data,
我们可能会丢失数据，
so we obviously need both servers to be online
所以，我们显然需要两台服务器都在线，
in order to reconstruct global key value store.
以便重建全局键值存储。
And so if we want to make the system more reliable,
所以，如果我们想让系统更可靠，
we can do what we know best which is to replicate the servers
我们可以做我们最了解的事情，即复制服务器，
and so we can use raft style replication,
所以我们可以使用 Raft 风格的复制，
or we can also use primary backup style replication.
或者，我们也可以使用主备份式复制。
Now the question is,
现在的问题是，
okay with all this replication, all this cryptographic machinery
好的，所有这些复制，所有这些加密机制，
and on this message routing,
在这条消息路由上，
can we still achieve good throughput,
我们还能实现很好的吞吐量吗，
and it turns out that we can actually paralyze the server step here,
事实证明，我们可以在这里并行服务器步骤，
that does proof checking navigation,
提供证明验证[]，
which is likely to be the bottleneck of the system
这很可能是系统的瓶颈，
and what's going to happen is that,
接下来会发生的是，
proxies are going to hash partition,
代理要对分区进行哈希，
their inputs to each of these servers
它们对每台服务器的输入，
and then each of these servers in reduce step,
然后这些服务器中的每一个都处于 reduce 步骤中，
will combine their intermediate key value stores
将合并它们的中间键值存储，
to reconstruct the global key value store containing all the sums.
以重建包含所有和的全局键值存储。
Okay?
好的？
And so now the final question is,
所以现在最后一个问题是，
did I implement all this before the due date,
我是不是在到期日之前实现了这个，
unfortunately, no,
很遗憾，没有,
but I did make it much of the way there,
但我确实走了很远的路，
so I'm gonna show a quick demo of the non replicated, non parallel version of it.
所以，我将展示一个简单的 domo ，
So I'm going to quickly switch to my other laptop,
所以我要快速切换到我的另一台笔记本电脑，
I gotta stop sharing this one first.
我得先停止分享这个。
Yes, cool,
是的，酷，
okay, so great,
好的，太棒了，
so, on these right two terminals are going to be with servers,
所以，在这两个右侧的终端上将安装服务器，
so I'm going to run them,
所以我要运行它们，
it is implemented in Rust,
它是用 Rust 实现的，
now I'm going to hook up these two properties in the middle,
现在我要把中间的这两个代理连接起来，
and then on the left terminal,
然后在左边的终端，
I'm just gonna simulate a thousand honest clients.
我只想模拟一千个诚实的客户端。
And what's happening is all the clients are generating their input sharing
现在的情况是，所有的客户端都在生成它们的输入共享，
and generating zero-knowledge proofs
以及生成零知识证明，
and sending them with proxies,
并通过代理发送它们，
and the proxies are simply forwarding them to the servers,
而代理只是将它们转发到服务器，
and then here finally on the server side,
最后，在服务器端，
they're going to be checking all the proofs
它们会检查所有的证明，
and if the inputs are in fact well formed,
如果这些输入是格式良好的，
it's going to add it to its local key value store
它将把它添加到本地键值存储中，
and then at some time later,
然后在一段时间之后，
when the servers want to reconstruct the final statistics,
当服务器想要重建最终统计数据时，
they can just combine their key value source to recover the sums.
它们只需结合它们的键值存储来恢复和。
And that's it for my presentation,
我的演讲到此结束，
I'm happy to take any questions.
我很乐意回答任何问题。
Do you have any questions from the audience?
观众有什么问题吗？
I guess I have a question,
我想我有个问题，
so like with what you implemented so far,
所以你到目前为止实现的那样，
what sort of, like which at what point do you accept,
比如什么你会接受，
what point do tolerate failures
什么容错，类似的东西，
Yeah, so the reliability of the current implementation is not great,
是的，所以现在实现的可靠性不是很高，
mostly because the servers aren't replicated,
主要是因为服务器没有被复制，
so for the proxies,
所以对于代理来说，
because, the clients broadcast the proxies,
因为，客户广播代理，
all you require is that one of the proxies is up,
你所需要的就是其中一个代理启动，
so if we have two proxies,
如果我们有两个代理，
we can tolerate one failure of the proxies
我们可以容忍一个代理失败，
and will still get the messages to the servers,
我们仍然会获得到服务器的消息，
but if any of the servers goes down,
但如果任何一台服务器出现故障，
then you're just not going to be reconstruct on the data for that.
那么你就不能根据这些数据进行重建了。
Is it only for sums
这只是对于和吗，
or did you implemented for any general function that operates on the all those inputs.
或者，你是否实现了对所有这些输入进行操作的任何通用函数？
Yeah, for now, I've only implemented for sums,
是的，目前，我只实现了和，
but basically with this additive secret sharing scheme,
但使用这种相加的秘密共享方案，
you can compute any linear function you want,
你可以计算任何你想要的线性函数，
and maybe more complex ones are possible,
也许更复杂的问题是可能的，
but I'm still haven't explored those yet,
但我还没有探索过这些，
it turns out at least in practice,
事实证明，至少在实践中，
sums probably get like 90% of the way there.
和可能会达到 90% 的水平。
So what do you performance numbers looked like?
那么，你的性能数据是什么样子的？
Performance numbers, yeah,
性能数字，是的，
so the main things we want to measure are,
所以我们想要衡量的主要事情是，
for the client side clients on computation and client bandwidth,
对于客户端，计算和客户端带宽，
I have some numbers,
我有一些数字，
at least for client computation,
至少对于客户端计算而言，
I'm generating these shares and these proofs takes less than a few milliseconds,
这些共享，而这些证明只需不到几毫秒，
so it's very lightweight,
所以它非常轻，
the bandwidth is just a few kilobytes,
带宽只有几千字节，
and then for the throughput on the server side,
然后对于服务器端的吞吐量，
but I only allocated four cores to each server,
但我只给每台服务器分配了四个核心，
because I only had 64 cores
因为我只有 64 个核心，
and I wanted most of them to be on the client,
我希望它们中的大多数都在客户端上，
so I could remove that bottleneck
这样我就能消除这个瓶颈，
and so at four cores,
所以，在四个核心上，
I think, what is that,
我想，那是什么，
probably like a thousand queries per second
可能每秒有一千个查询，
and then estimating I guess if you paralyze by twenty servers for each logical machine,
然后估计，我猜如果每台机器并行 20 台服务器，
they can probably achieve close to 22000 queries per second,
它们可能每秒可以实现近 22000 次查询，
but this is all run on the same data center,
但这些都是在同一个数据中心运行的，
so it doesn't factor into latency,
所以，它不会影响延迟，
so the actual numbers will probably be a little bit lower than that.
实际数字可能会比这个数字低一点。
I had a question about your implementation,
我对你的实现有一个问题，
how do you do, so how do you actually implement your knowledge proofs and code not theoretical.
你如何，
Yeah, that's a great question,
是的，这是个很好的问题，
I can send you the paper, that I implemented it out,
我可以把我实现的论文发送给你，
but it's it's not too complicated,
但这并不太复杂，
basically it's just a bunch of finite field operations
基本上，它只是一堆有限域运算，
and so if you find your file library,
如果你找到你的文件库，
just follow the paper and follow the steps
只要按照论文，遵循步骤，
and it's so much straightforward from that point,
从这一点上来说，这是非常简单的，
as long as you can decrypt the paper.
只要你能解密那个论文。
Okay, and is that and is it possible to like test that,
好的，有没有可能测试它，
like, like, how would you know that it's working or not working.
你怎么知道它起作用了还是没有起作用。
Yeah, so I guess,
是的，所以我想，
yeah, I only showed the simulation with a honest clients,
是的，我只展示了诚实的客户端模拟，
but you can also generate a simulation with clients that submit bad proofs
但是，你也可以生成与提交错误证据的客户的模拟，
and then you can see them being rejected.
然后你可以看到它们被拒绝了。
Okay, yeah, that makes sense, thank you.
好的，是的，有道理，谢谢。
Yeah.
好的。
Great, thanks, pretty sweet,
好的，谢谢，很[]，
is the next group ready to go?
下一组准备好了吗？
Hello, I'm Shannon and Nik and Johan on here,
大家好，我是 Shannen 和 Nik Johan ，
so Johan take it away.
所以 Johan 请开始。
Thank you, Shannon,
谢谢， Shannen ，
so we'll be talking about BukaDocs,
所以我们将谈论 BukaDocs ，
BukaDocs is a distributive collaborative editor,
BukaDocs 是一个分布式协同编辑器，
it's similar to Google docs,
它类似于 Google Docs ，
just a little bit better,
只是稍微好一点，
so to move onto the next slide,
所以，进入下一张幻灯片，
can you look next for them.
你能看到下一个吗？
Okay, so as you've seen in this class,
好的，就像你们在这节课上看到的，
achieving consistency is very hard to do in the distributed system,
在分布式系统中实现一致性是非常困难的，
there are many ways that consistency could go wrong,
一致性可能会在很多方面出错，
so a very simple example is,
所以一个非常简单的例子是，
if the order that you received RPCs is different in each peer,
如果你在每个节点中收到 RPC 的顺序不同，
you might end up with an inconsistent state,
你可能会得到一个不一致的状态，
and there's a data structure called CRDTs,
还有一种叫做 CRDT 的数据结构，
which we use in our system to mitigate this issue,
我们在我们的系统中使用它来缓解这个问题，
CRDTs achieve eventually consistency,
CRDT 实现最终一致性，
by making every single operation that you make on the document,
通过对文档进行每一次操作，
globally unique,
全局唯一的，不仅对每个节点唯一，而是全局唯一的，
so if I press the letter a on my editor,
所以如果我在编辑器输入字母 a ，
it's different from Shannon or Nik pressing the letter a on their editor,
不同于 Shannen 或 Nik 在他们的编辑器输入字母 a ，
so, for example here even if the bottom here,
所以，举个例子，在底部这里，
for example here adds a new turtle to a document,
例如，这里将一个新的海龟添加到文档中，
even if they receive remove request from the other two peers,
即使它们接收到来自其他两个节点的移除请求，
they will never remove the golden turtle,
它们永远不会移走金海龟，
because the operation is itself different from remove,
因为这个操作本身不同于删除，
so remove green turtle is different from remove gold turtle.
所以移除绿海龟和移除金海龟是不同的。
And this, this is how we achieve eventual consistency,
这就是我们实现最终一致性的方式，
so from here, I believe Nik is going to talk a little bit more about what is here,
所以从这里开始，
how we implement [] [entities].
我们如何实现第三种方式。
Yeah, so for Bukadocs, we chose to use a CRDT called LSEQ,
是的，所以对于 BukaDocs ，
which represents a sequence of elements with variable length keys,
表示具有可变长度密钥的元素序列，
so the goal is,
所以我们的目标是，
let's say we want a sequence that represents the alphabet
假设我们想要一个表示字母表的序列，
and so far we have the letters a and c,
到目前为止，我们有字母 a 和 c ，
so one editor might choose to try adding the letter b between them
一位编辑者可能会选择尝试在它们之间添加字母 b ，
and another editor may choose to try adding the letter d after c,
而另一编辑者可以选择尝试在 c 之后添加字母 d ，
and the goal is that with eventual consistency,
目标是最终的一致性，
will eventually reach the state a b c d,
最终会到达状态 a b c d ，
so the way that LSEQ achieves this is,
所以， LSEQ 实现这一点的方式是，
by using a START and END token,
通过使用开始和结束 token ，
and then it gives every character in the document an individual token,
然后它给文档中的每个字符一个单独的 token ，
that is between the start and the end,
在 START 和 END 之间，
so we can insert h between start end,
所以我们可以在 START 和 END 之间插入 h ，
if we want the letter i after h,
如果我们想要 i 在 h 之后，
then we can insert that at 7, which is between 4 and end,
我们可以把它插入到 7 ，
now, if we want to insert an exclamation point between i and the end of the document,
现在，如果我们想在 i 和文档末尾之间插入一个感叹号，
we can insert it with the key 7 2,
我们可以把它插入到键 7,2 ，
so we increase key length or two to create key between two other keys that are adjacent,
因此我们增加键[]到 2 ，
so in this way, we can always create a key between any two other keys,
通过这种方式，我们始终可以在任何两个其他键之间创建一个键，
so we can always insert,
所以我们可以随时插入，
now LSEQ forms well,
现在 LSEQ 很好地形成了，
in that it reaches eventual consistency with very little effort for coordination,
它以很少的协调努力达到了最终的一致性，
and it has some optimizations that cause the length of the keys to grow relatively slowly.
它还进行了一些优化，
However, some cons are that in order to support deletion of these elements,
然而，一些缺点是，
it relies on causal delivery and exactly-once delivery,
它依赖于因果交付和恰好一次交付，
and we didn't really want to implement this,
我们并不想实现这个，
since it was based off a number of other works,
因为它是给予其他一些工作的，
so we use a slightly simpler approach, which was a deletion set,
所以我们使用一种稍微简单一些的方法，
so this is a grow only set, where we add in elements,
这是一个仅增长的集合，我们在其中添加元素，
so for instance to delete letters h and i,
所以，例如删除字母 h 和 i ，
we would add in 4 7 into this deletion set,
我们会把 4 7 添加到这个删除集中，
then this whole state becomes equivalent to just having to start and end tokens
然后，整个状态相当于只需要 START 和 END token ，
and the exclamation point at key 7 2.
感叹号在键 7,2 。
So we built the Buka docs service
所以我们建立了 Buka Docs 服务，
similar to how we implemented kv raft,
类似于我们实现 kv Raft 的方式，
we have multiple servers, multiple clients
我们有多个服务器，多个客户端，
and multiple clients, they only talk to one server at a time
多个客户端，它们一次只与一台服务器通信，
and they continuously try the operations until they get a successful reply from the server,
它们不断尝试操作，
clients and servers both maintain an AVL tree of characters in the document,
客户端和服务器都维护文档中的字符的 AVL 树，
as well as our own deletion set of removed keys,
以及我们自己删除的删除键集合，
we chose to store characters in AVL tree,
我们选择将字符存储在 AVL 树中，
for I guess performance reasons,
我猜是出于性能原因，
the chain of events goes something like this,
事件的链条大概是这样的，
so the client will send an insertion and deletion to the server,
客户端将向服务器发送插入和删除，
a server will update its own AVL tree and deletion set and persist that,
服务器将更新其自己的 AVL 树和删除集，并持久化保存，
and for those updates to all the other servers and clients
对于所有其他服务器和客户端的更新，
and then the server will respond success to the client.
然后服务器会向客户端响应成功。
So we're going to demo it,
所以我们要演示一下，
we build a very simple UI for it here,
我们在这里为它构建了一个非常简单的用户界面，
so let me give it,
所以让我来，
Johan and Nik are also accessing this from different clients right now,
Johan 和 Nik 现在也在从不同的客户访问这个，
so you can see them typing,
所以你可以看到他们的输入，
you can type something else,
你可以输入其他内容，
I'm typing here,
我在这里输入，
I think Johan is typing hi,
我想 Johan 是在输入 hi ，
Nik is typing something here,
Nik 在输入一些东西，
and we can edit each others text as well.
我们还可以编辑彼此的文本。
Then, yeah, that is Buka Docs,
那么，是的，这就是 Buka Docs ，
we're happy to answer any questions, I guess.
我们很乐意回答任何问题。
I have a question here,
我有一个问题，
I really like the turtle theme,
我很喜欢海龟的主题，
that you guys came up with this
你们想出了这个，
and I was just wondering where the, where the turtle theme came from.
我只是想知道海龟的主题是从哪里来的？
Oh yeah, so the turtle is Nik Johan and I also taught the class over IP
哦，是的，海龟是 Nik Johan 和我通过网络讨论课程，
and the turtle is our mascot for the class
海龟是我们课程的吉祥物，
and we are inspired to build Buka docs,
我们受到启发，构建 Buka Docs ，
because we use Google docs is a question document for the students ask questions,
因为我们使用的 Google Docs 是一个问题文档，
but it couldn't handle a load of over 75 users typing at the same time
它无法同时处理超过 75 个用户的输入，
and that's how Buka docs was born.
Buka Docs 就是这样诞生的。
Thank you for ask.
谢谢你的提问。
That's cool.
那很酷。
I had a quick question,
我有一个简短的问题，
and so first of all, I got called little presentation,
所以首先，我调用了这个演示，
sorry, if you mentioned this, you may have,
抱歉，如果你提到这一点，你可能已经，
but so first of all, first question just to make sure I understood correctly,
但首先，第一个问题是，为了确保我理解正确，
is the are these data structures which are very interesting,
这些数据结构非常有趣，
they stored on the client or the server,
它们存储在客户端或服务器上，
if they're stored, on I imagine right now the server is not replicated,
如果它们被存储了，
but that's something you could easily do,
但这是你可以很容易做到的事情，
but if they if they are stored on the client,
但如果它们存储在客户端上，
what happens if one of the clients fails.
如果其中一个客户端出现故障会发生什么情况？
So the data structures are actually stored on all the clients and all the servers,
所以，数据结构存储在所有客户端和所有服务器上，
and so right now, we're assuming the clients are fully trustworthy,
现在，我们假设客户端是完全值得信任的，
and so if client fails, any edits they haven't sent to a server,
所以，如果客户端出现故障，
will just be on their end until they come back online,
会一直在它们那边，
in which case they can send it
在这种情况下，它们可以发送
and it will achieve eventual consistency.
它将实现最终的一致性。
Interesting, thank you.
很有趣，谢谢。
Oh, I had a question,
哦，我有个问题，
why LSEQ over other CRDTs.
为什么 LSEQ 胜过其他 CRDT ？
Yeah, we chose LSEQ mainly just because,
是的，我们选择 LSEQ 主要是因为，
it was one of the first ones we found
这是我们最先发现的，
and we wanted to get started
我们想要开始，
and because after implementing the logic of the variable length keys,
因为在实现可变长度键的逻辑之后，
there was really not much more,
没有太多我们需要做的，
that the clients and servers stayed consistent.
客户端和服务器保持一致。
Oh, okay, thank you.
哦，好的，谢谢。
So beyond that it was just like message passing
除此之外，它就像是消息传递，
and making sure everyone gets all the messages.
并确保每个人都收到了所有的信息。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
So, how many servers are you running within this example,
那么，在这个示例中，你运行了多少台服务器，
was it just one or was it multiple?
是只有一个还是多个？
There were three servers and three clients,
有三台服务器和三台客户端，
each one of the clients was connected to known to its own server.
每个客户端都连接到自己已知的服务器。
So you are using the servers for scaling or for fault tolerance, or both?
所以，你使用服务器用于扩展或容错，还是两者都有？
A little bit for both,
两者都有，
when we ran the performance metrics,
当我们运行性能指标时，
by distributing the load of the client requests across many servers,
通过将客户端请求的负载分布在多个服务器上，
you are able to handle a little bit more bandwidth request,
你可以处理稍微多一点的带宽请求，
however, this is a trade-off between,
然而，这是一种权衡，
because eventual consistency will take a little bit more time,
因为最终一致性将需要更多的时间，
because the servers will have to send RPCs,
因为服务器将必须发送 RPC 到每一台其他服务器，
so our paper, we have a whole diagram everything, but.
所以在我们的论文上，我们有一个完整的图表，但是。
Yeah, how well does it scale,
好的，它的规模有多大，
as you add more servers.
随着你添加更多的服务器。
Yeah, so have the metrics on my other screen,
是的，我的另一个屏幕上有指标，
so it's able to handle,
所以它能够处理，
if we gave it to more or less 3000 requests across five clients and five servers,
如果我们将其分配给五个客户端和五个服务器上的 3000 个请求，
it achieve eventual consistency within three seconds,
它在三秒内实现了最终一致性，
but this was mainly because it was also on a computer,
但这主要是因为它在计算机上，
that's on local host with RPCs were really fast.
在本地主机上， RPC 速度非常快。
However, that also means that all the computers happening on one machine,
然而，这也意味着所有的计算机都在一台机器上运行，
so this can go either way when we put it on real hardware.
所以，当我们把它放在真正的硬件上时，是两种方式。
Yeah, another thing is that,
是的，还有一件事是，
if you make too many requests at once,
如果你一次提出太多请求，
eventually consistency kind of hard to achieve,
最终一致性很难实现，
so for example we tried to do 19000 edits at once,
例如，我们试图一次进行 19000 次编辑，
across a hundred clients and five servers
通过 100 个客户端和 5 台服务器，
and it took around 32 seconds to reach eventual consistency,
它花了大约 32 秒才达到最终一致性，
however, if we only did 3000 edits across a hundred clients and five servers,
然而，如果我们只在 100 个客户端和 5 个服务器上进行 3000 次编辑，
it only took around three seconds.
这只花了大约三秒钟。
When you say you do whatever the 19000 or whatever that was,
当你说你做了 19000 或其他的事，
is that like sending all those at once,
就是一次发送所有这些信息，
or is it spread out over time.
或者它是随着时间的推移而扩散的。
Every single one is sent, every single edit sent in parallel, and at least at test.
每一个单独发送，
Interesting.
有意思。
I had a quick question,
我有一个简短的问题，
so one of the motivators
所以其中一个激励因素，
that collaborative text editors like Google docs can't support high scale updates concurrent updates,
像 Google Docs 这样的协作文本编辑器
so why don't you think they use an approach like what you guys are proposing.
所以你认为他们为什么不采用你们所提议的方法？
I think Google docs uses a similar approach called operational transform,
我认为 Google Docs 使用了一种类似的方法，称为操作转换，
which I'm not sure, if it can be parallelized as well,
我不确定，它是否也可以并行，
and they probably don't want to,
他们可能不想这么做，
because they don't want to give us that much server power,
因为他们不想提供那么多的服务器能力，
it's probably just like for cost effectiveness,
这可能只是为了成本效益，
I'm guessing.
我猜。
Yeah, I'm just, how [] say,
是的，我只是，怎么说，
I don't think they use case a hundred people editing one document,
我不认为上百个人编辑一个文档的情况，
comes up too often,
出现得很频繁，
at least in the Google Google docs usage,
至少在 Google Docs 的使用中，
so it's probably not something you want to spend extra engineering time on.
所以，可能不想在这方面花费额外的工程时间。
Great, thank you, cool demo,
好的，谢谢，很酷的 demo 。
so up next, we have the eggscrambler,
所以接下来，我们有 eggscrambler ，
if you all ready.
如果你们准备好了。
Cool, hello everyone, my name is Arvid
好的，大家好，我叫 Arvid ，
and together with Arman and Wendy,
和 Arman 和 Wendy 一起，
we have been working on eggscrambler,
我们研究的是 eggscrambler ，
which is anonymous broadcasting using community encryption.
这是使用交换加密的匿名广播。
So let's start with a motivating problem,
所以让我们从一个动机问题开始，
we all know we all love MIT Confessions,
我们都喜欢 MIT Confessions ，
so let's say that one person in this class wants to submit a confession,
假设班上有一个人想要提交一个 confession ，
telling people how much they love this class,
告诉人们他们有多喜欢这门课，
and so what do they do,
那么他们会做些什么，
well they submit this convention to a Google form,
他们把这个 confession 提交给 Google Forms ，
and then that goes to the MIT Confessions admin
然后交给 MIT Confessions 管理员，
and then that hopefully goes to the Facebook page,
然后这些信息可能进入 Facebook 页面。
but now let's consider a scenario,
但现在让我们来考虑一个场景，
where the confessions admin is actually an MIT professor,
confessions 管理员是 MIT 的教授，
particularly for another classic course,
特别是对于另一门经典课程来说，
so obviously they would not want this confession to be posted,
所以很明显他们不希望这个 confession 被贴出来，
so they would [censor] it,
所以他们会审查它，因为他们可以，
but it's like even worse,
但更糟糕的是，
because they could they could there like an MIT professor,
因为他们可以，作为 MIT 的教授，
so they could go to Google look at their network traffic,
这样他们可以去 Google 查看他们的网络流量，
they could look at the MIT WiFi network traffic,
他们可以查看 MIT WiFi 网络流量，
so they could figure out who actually sent this,
这样他们就能找出是谁发的这个，
and then obviously they would like to give that person an f minus in their class
很明显，他们想在班上给那个人打个 F- ，
and that's terrible,
这太可怕了。
so what do we want to do,
那么我们想要做什么，
well, we want anonymous broadcasting
我们想要匿名广播，
and that's like a common theme today,
这看起来是今天的一个共同主题，
well, we define it as a protocol to broadcast a message to everyone,
我们把它定义为向每个人广播消息的协议，
so without further do,
所以，我们进一步的工作，
I will let Wendy talk about how we do that.
我会让 Wendy 说说我们是怎么做的。
So yeah, the two main features of our design are that,
所以，我们设计的两个主要特点是，
it is decentralized and uses cryptography,
它是去中心化的，并使用密码学，
in particular, community of encryption is necessary,
尤其是，交换加密是必要，
because otherwise the description order will reveal the original identities of message senders.
因为否则描述顺序
Yeah, so here's the protocol be implemented,
是的，所以这就是我们要实现的协议，
ensure participants join the network
确保参与者加入网络，
and encrypt and submit their message,
加密和提交他们的消息，
which [winds] up encrypted by all participants exactly once in the encrypt phase,
它在加密阶段中由所有参与者恰好加密一次，
the scramble phase provides anonymity,
加扰阶段提供匿名性，
because as highlighted,
因为正如突出显示的那样，
because every participant encrypts the messages
因为每个参与者都对消息进行加密，
and randomize is there order,
随机化是有秩序的，
finally decryption results in the desired list of messages from all participants with no connection to identity.
最后，解密会得到所需的消息列表，
So yeah, if all participants are honest,
所以，如果所有参与者都是诚实的，
this protocol successfully results in anonymity,
这个协议成功地导致了匿名性，
while it is possible for a malicious user to determine the sender of a message,
虽然恶意用户可能确定消息的发送者，
we believe that such actions are detectable upon massacre reveals,
我们相信这样的行为是可以检测到的，
if people are interested,
如果人们感兴趣，
there exist other solutions to this problems,
对于这个问题还有其他解决方案，
such as mix-nets and DC-nets,
例如混合网络和DC网络，
next Armand will describe the structure of the implementation.
接下来， Arman 将描述实现的结构。
So, first of all, look at this assuming that,
所以，首先，看看这个假设，
we're looking at the high-level interface for,
我们看到的是高级别接口，
someone trying to submit a message
有人试图提交消息，与我们服务器的交互，
so let's say you're the person trying to submit a confession,
假设你是那个想要提交 confession 的人，
you're this application client,
你是这个应用程序客户端，
so the first thing you're going to do is send a start message,
所以你要做的第一件事就是发送一条 Start 消息，
so that indicates that you want to start a new broadcast round,
这表明你想要开始新的广播，
and the service is going to ask all the people
Service 将询问所有人，
who are participating in the round for a message,
谁是这轮的参与者，通过一个信息，
and then it's going to run this protocol
然后它将运行这个协议，
and then it's going to send the results to everyone who participated
然后它会将结果发送给所有参与的人，
or if it's something like confessions going to publish it,
或者如果是 confession 发布它，
and I feel at this point, it would be anonymized,
在这一点上，它将是匿名的，
but this is a very simple view,
但这是一个非常简单的观点，
in reality, we're actually building this on top of our raft implementation from the labs,
事实上，
so the reason we use lab raft is two [],
所以我们使用实验 Raft 的原因是两个，
so one, we implement the protocol as a state machine,
第一，我们将协议实现为状态机，
and so raft is among many instances that are running the protocol
所以， Raft 是运行这个协议的众多实例之一，
and so raft is used to replicate this state
Raft 用来复制这种状态，
and then two, when we're doing the scramble phase,
然后第二，当我们做打乱阶段时，
we need to make sure that each participant is scrambling in a specific order,
我们需要确保每个参与者都以特定的顺序进行打乱，
so we actually use raft as a coordination mechanism
所以我们使用 Raft 作为一种协调机制，
to do this test and set,
做这个 test-and-set ，
where they all proceed in a single order,
在那里，它们以单一的顺序进行，
so similar to the kv store,
所以类似于 kv 存储，
we have the state machine server,
我们有状态机服务器，
that's reading the raft updates
它读取 Raft 的更新，并更新状态机，
and we also add in the state machine client,
我们还添加了状态机客户端，
which is reading how the state machine is changing
它读取状态机是如何改变的，
and then this client is what's actually taking the actions
然后这个客户真正采取行动
to progress the protocol in some way,
以某种方式推进协议，
and then again just as in kv store,
然后，就像在 kv 存储中，
in order to progress the protocol,
为了推进协议，
this client is going to contact the leader server,
这个客户端将联系 Leader 服务器，
with a request to the state machine updates,
使用对状态机更新的请求，
and then we also implement the raft configuration change RPCs,
然后我们还实现了 raft 配置变更 RPC ，
so servers can add or remove themselves to the configuration,
服务器可以在配置中添加或删除自身，
and this means that,
这意味着，
new people can join subsequent broadcast rounds
新人可以加入随后的几轮广播，
and then also if there's a failure,
然后，如果出现故障，
we can cut someone out of the configuration,
我们可以把某人从配置中删除，
so that the next broadcast round can proceed,
这样下一轮广播才能继续进行，
because our protocol requires that everyone is actually active in order for the round to complete,
因为我们的协议要求每个人都是活跃的，
and then finally we have the application,
然后我们终于有了应用程序，
where the client is like something like confessions running on your phone,
客户端就像是在你手机上运行的 confession ，
will send these broadcast messages to the clients
会将这些广播消息发送给客户端，
and then it will receive the update,
然后它会收到更新，
once the protocol has completed.
一旦协议完成。
So we're going to show a quick demo recorded,
所以，我们将播放一段录制的快速演示，
just let me know if you can't hear this,
如果你听不到的话，就告诉我。
So now onto the demo,
现在我们来看演示，
we start working at Wendy's computer right now
我们现在开始在 Wendy 的计算机上工作，
and she's going to start the application,
她将启动应用程序，
so she's basically gonna start an instance on her computer and try
所以她在计算机上启动一个实例，并尝试，
and she's currently sending the link for her configuration into the zoom chat
她正在将她的配置链接发送到 Zoom 聊天中，
as we can see here,
正如我们在这里看到的，
so now we're gonna go to Arvid's computer,
所以现在我们要进入 Arvid 的计算机，
he's gonna take that link and enjoy the same configuration as Wendy,
他会利用这个链接，
so he does that,
所以他这么做了，
and now he's going to start the round,
现在他要开始这一轮，
will can send their messages,
好的，可以发送他们的信息，
and we have the round succeeded,
我们的这一轮已经成功了。
so now are we going to show that we can seamlessly add a new client,
现在我们要展示可以无缝添加新客户端，
so this is both someone is going to send a message
所以这两个都会发出一条信息，
and an entirely new raft instance,
一个全新的 Raft 实例，
so we see here,
所以我们在这里看到，
this new instance quickly catches up on the left there,
这个新实例很快就赶上了左边的那个，
and now all three of them are going to send a message for this next round,
现在他们三人都将为下一轮传递一个信息，
and we get all three messages,
我们收到了所有三条信息，
so we demonstrated that we can broadcast over the network
所以我们演示了我们可以通过网络进行广播
and also add in clients at will.
还可以随意添加客户。
Yes, that's a demo of eggscrambler,
是的，这是 eggscrambler 的演示，
does anyone have any questions?
有没有人有什么问题？
This is this is a really fast one,
这是一张非常快的一个，
this first of all, this is a really cool system,
首先，这是一个非常酷的系统，
well, so the application is separate from the client raft state machine, correct.
那么，应用程序与客户端 Raft 状态机是分开的，对吗？
Yes.
是的。
And it's like two different devices,
这就像是两个不同的设备，
so I guess my question sort of is,
所以我想我的问题是，
like in the overall picture of how you would deploy this thing,
你如何部署这个东西的整体图景，
why is that,
为什么会这样呢，
I mean I imagine you could run a like a raft state machine with a bunch of phones,
我的意思是，我想象你可以
it might be poor availability,
它可能可用性较差，
but you've implemented the configuration changes,
但你已经实现了配置更改，
so in principle could that,
所以原则上可以这样做，
really, I'm just trying to figure out what the role of the client is,
真的，我只是想弄清楚客户端的角色是什么，
in this whole thing, the server is a cluster of servers that makes sense,
在这整个过程中，
the applications that make sense, but.
应用程序也有意义，但是。
So basically the client,
所以客户端，
it's basically just like a nice way to like write the implementation,
这是编写实现的一种不错的方式，
so the server and the client,
所以服务器和客户端，
you can basically think of that as a server,
你可以把它想象成一台服务器，
is just like in our implementation,
在我们的实现中，
it made sense to create this abstraction, yeah.
创造这个抽象概念是有意义的，是的。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
In order for the round to progress,
为了让这轮取得进展，
all peers must receive the message from all the other peers where n-1 peers
所有节点必须从所有其他节点接收消息，
and so if you have some very weird partition,
所以如果你有一些非常奇怪的分区，
where like some subset is able to talk to the rest of the subset,
某些子集不能与其余部分子集交互，
how would that be resolved here?
这个问题将如何在这里解决？
Yeah, so if you, if you like partition into like smaller than,
是的，所以如果分区在，
then then it would just be stuck forever,
然后它就会永远卡住，
until you find a majority
直到你找到多数，
and then once you have a majority,
一旦你获得了多数，
you can like they, they automatically submit,
它们会自动提交，
like remove server RPCs,
比如删除服务器 RPC ，
whenever they don't get a response from someone,
当它们得不到某人的回应时，
so then the cluster like shrinks until like the non responding nodes disappeared.
然后，集群会缩小，
I noticed in the demo example you gave,
我注意到在你给出的演示示例中，
you had one person who wrote two of the messages
你有一个写了两条信息，
and so, someone else who wrote the third message
另一个写了第三条信息，
and that meant that you could that the person who wrote two messages
这意味着你可以，
could always tell what that third person had shared,
总是能确定第三个人分享了什么，
doesn't that sort of defeat the purpose of your protocol.
这是不是有点违背了你的协议的目的？
Yeah, yeah, so the reason why it was two messages,
是的，所以为什么它是两条信息，
because we're running, we're running both of those instances on the same computer,
因为我们运行，
that is, that is an attack though where,
这是一个攻击，在那里，
you know you have it,
你拥有它，
you start around where one person is controlled by everyone,
你从一个人被所有人控制的地方开始，
well like five of the servers
比如五台服务器，
and five of them submitting messages are controlled by everyone,
其中五个提交信息的人被每个人控制，
and you know who the last person is,
你知道最后一个人是谁，
but, I think so we currently consider that like a byzantine or non byzantine failures,
但是，我认为我们目前认为
so the clients are acting honestly
所以客户端的行为是诚实的，
and they're not trying to gain an unfair amount of advantage in the system
它们并没有试图在系统中获得不公平的优势，
and the attacker or someone who's listening to all the network traffic.
以及攻击者或监听所有网络流量的人。
Okay, so you're not worried about people involved in the system undermining it,
好的，所以你并不担心系统中涉及的人破坏它，
you're only worried about people who are like peeking in on the system and driving it.
你只会担心那些人
Yeah.
是的。
Or like kind of,
或者就像是，
so I think we're like decently confident that,
所以我认为我们很有信心，
like a if if they're byzantine participants,
如果他们是拜占庭式的参与者，
then, the protocol will fail
然后，协议将失败，它会失败，
but it's like there are so many different absolutely not exactly certain that that is the case,
但有一些不同的，
but we think so,
但我们认为是这样，
but it's like it's.
但这就像是。
So for the attack that got discussed then,
所以对于当时讨论的袭击，
where someone takes control of the cluster
其中有人控制了集群，
and but it takes over all the
但它接管了所有，
and essentially is all of the clients, except for one of them,
基本上是所有的客户端，除了它们中的一个，
and if you're a leader,
如果你是领导者，你可以控制，
you could make that happen,
你可以做到这一点，
would that be detected by your current system.
你们目前的系统能检测到吗？
No, no, not not when it's like n-1,
不，不，当它是 n-1 的时候不会，
so we need at least two,
所以我们至少需要两个，
if we have two honest people,
如果我们有两个诚实的人，
then that would be enough,
那就足够了，
because they would be like if they were disconnected from each other,
因为它们会，
they could know that.
他们可能知道这个。
Alright cool, thank you.
好的，很好，谢谢。
Overtime, thanks very cool,
超出时间，谢谢，很酷，
maybe a MIT concession will reach out,
也许 MIT confession 会出现。
let's hear from the fault tolerance project,
让我们来听听容错项目，
maybe that's a bad way of summarizing.
也许这是一种糟糕的总结方式。
No worries.
别担心。
Yeah, everyone, I'm Ariel,
好的，大家好，我是 Ariel ，
I've been working on this project with Frans for a bit now,
我做这个项目[]已经有一段时间了，
so let's see I can share my screen.
让我们看看我能不能分享屏幕。
And so, yeah as you can see here,
所以，是的，正如你在这里看到的，
a project involves giving fault tolerance for free at the 9P interface
项目涉及在 9P 接口上免费提供容错，
and also break down what this means exactly and extra slides,
并详细分析这意味着什么和额外的幻灯片。
we start by looking at service computation,
我们先来看看无服务计算，
so if you've heard of some things like AWS lambda or GCP also Google cloud functions,
如果你听说过 AWS Lambda
essentially what this does is,
从本质上讲，它所做的是，
instead of having to set a bunch of VMs
不是必须设置一堆虚拟机，并扩展，
you can just write a small stateless function,
你可以只编写一个小的无状态函数，
do you oppose your application through a bunch of small stateless functions,
通过一堆小的无状态函数来开发你的应用程序，
which are triggered over http requests,
通过 HTTP 请求触发，
and then AWS or Google cloud or who are your service providers will handle the scaling
然后， AWS 或 Google 云或你的服务提供商
and this is nice,
这很好，
because in theory operators can balance resources more effectively,
因为理论上运营商可以更有效地平衡资源，
they can get high utilization,
它们可以获得很高的利用率，
and in theory it's easier for developers as well,
从理论上，这对开发人员来说也更容易，
all you have to do is,
你所要做的就是，
is you don't have to worry about all this kind of infrastructure management
你不必担心所有这些基础设施管理，
and sort of having enough headroom
并且有足够的[净空]数量虚拟机或任何东西，
and everything to handle spikes in customer load and things like this.
处理客户负载激增等问题的一切措施。
However, the reality is not as nice as the theory,
然而，现实并不像理论那么美好，
which is in the end,
也就是说，到最后，
in current implementations,
在当前的实现中，
actually building these complex applications is quite difficult,
构建这些复杂的应用程序是相当困难的，
and decomposing them into these state functions quite difficult,
将它们分解成这些无状态函数相当困难，
in part because these lambdas these stateless functions lack rich communication primitives,
因为这些 Lambdas ，
which would be important support to build complex applications,
这是构建复杂应用程序的重要支持，
so they can't directly communicate or through to each other,
所以它们不能直接通信，
therefore systems that try to utilize serverless functions,
因此，试图利用无服务器函数的系统，
have had to sort of build their own custom communication solutions,
不得不构建自己的定制通信解决方案，
like maybe setting up the ends on the side,
比如把两端放在边上，
that they round everyone talk through
他们围着那个通信，
or talking through a storage systems, like S3
或者通过存储系统进行通信，比如 S3 ，
and this makes them efficient and difficult for developers to actually put together in a sensible way,
这使得它们变得低效，
all this complexity causes data centers to actually manage resources quite poor,
所有这些复杂性导致数据中心管理资源相当糟糕，
and and the problem is that,
问题是，
we still have all these data center resources segmented into a bunch of local name spaces,
我们仍然将所有这些数据中心资源
which are destroyed and and you can't share resources across them.
它们是[]，
So what we were looking at was reviving some work from past decades called Plan9
所以，我们正在研究的是
and Plan9 are essentially provides plan for unifying data center resources
Plan9 提供了统一数据中心资源的方案，
and providing a single system image,
并提供单个系统映像，
what this means essentially when you write your application,
这意味着，当你编写你的应用程序时，
you don't have to worry about what runs on what machines,
你不必担心什么东西在什么机器上运行，
about provisioning VMs or anything like that,
关于调配虚拟机或类似的内容，
or making sure that certain parts of the application on certain VMs,
或确保某些 VM 上的应用程序的某些部分，
it all looks like one giants are name space to your application,
对于你的应用程序，它看起来就像一个巨大的命名空间，
so your application knows nothing about what hardware it's actually running on
所以，你的应用程序完全不知道它运行在什么硬件上，
or where other services are in the data centre,
或者在数据中心的其他服务，
the ways achieved is applications services communicate through a global hierarchical namespace,
实现的方式是
services and resources to expose uniform file system like interface,
服务和资源暴露统一的文件系统类接口，
you don't have to worry about implementing and calling customer RPCs,
你不必担心实现和调用定制 RPC 。
and so for example and this, in this tree,
例如，在这棵树上，
you can see here,
你可以在这里看到，
we have the top level root level name space,
我们有顶级的根级名称空间，
and then under that we have three services registered,
然后我们有三个注册的服务，
we have an S3 service,
我们有 S3 服务，
which you can use to connect your [landers] to S3,
你可以用来把你的 Lambdas 连接到 S3 ，
you can access keys, S3 keys and values through that,
你可以通过它访问 S3 键和值，
we have an in-memory file system and sched
我们还有内存中的文件系统（memfs）和 sched ，
and so quickly.
所以，很快地。
Yeah, so this is what the what like a typical 9P name space would look like,
是的，这就是典型的 9P 名称空间是什么样子。
we have done some work to implement example of of this 9P architecture,
我们已经做了一些工作来实现
we have a, zookeeper like configuration service,
我们有一个类似 Zookeeper 的配置服务，
which hosts the top level name space,
它有顶级名称空间，
we have a scheduler and a bunch of these np servers, 9P servers,
我们有一个调度器和一堆 9P 服务器，
what these do is they expose resources and functionality
它们所做的是，
this three part of name space,
这个命名空间的 S3 部分，
you can write a service which connected S3 buckets
你可以编写连接 S3 存储的服务，
and and expose it to 9P and this would be a 9P server.
并将其暴露给 9P ，
And the RPCs or the operations that used to interact with these different services
那些 RPC 或操作
are all the 9P operations,
都是 9P 操作，
so it's a very small, well defined set of operations,
所以这是一个非常小的，定义很好的一组操作，
that, you can see a few of them here,
你可以在这里看到它们中的一些，
such as read and write moves that small number of canonical file system operations.
例如 Read Write Remove Stat ，
I so quickly done, what this looks like,
我快速展示一下它是什么样子，
so for example here,
例如，在这里，
I can start up correct infrastructure.
我可以启动基础设施。
So I can look into,
这样我可以查看，
you can map this name space right into Linux,
你可以将这个名称空间映射到 Linux 中，
so I can see some services
这样我就能看到一些服务，
and different name spaces that we've mounted here,
以及我们在这里挂载的不同的名称空间，
for example if I look at S3,
例如，如果我看一下 S3 ，
this is actually connecting to S3 bucket that we have,
这连接到我们拥有的 S3 存储桶，
I'm sorry do you actually see the keys in the S3 bucket,
你看到 S3 桶里的键了吗，
just as files in your file system,
就像文件系统中的文件一样，
and this is S3 bucket over here,
这是 S3 桶在这里，
so if I want to create, write a new key,
所以如果我想创建，写入一个新的键，
so instead of having to use AWS custom library,
所以，不必使用 AWS 定制库，
in order to so write S3,
为了写入 S3 ，
I can just write a file system module,
我可以只写入一个文件系统，
file system operation to create a file and write to it
执行一个文件系统操作来创建文件并写入它，
and then S3, this actually should show up as a new key now,
然后在 S3 ，现在应该显示一个新的键，
so we have test456, which we just wrote.
所以我们有了 test456 ，我们刚刚写的。
So, um, what does fault tolerance part coming here,
那么，这里容错部分是什么意思，
well as I mentioned before,
就像我之前提到的，
all these 9P services have a very well defined uniform interface,
所有这些 9P 服务都具有定义良好的统一接口，
there are no customer RPCs,
没有定制的 RPC ，
and this gives us a very unique opportunity,
这给了我们一个非常独特的机会，
which is we can slice at this 9P interface to replicate unmodified services,
我们可以在这个 9P 接口上切片，用来复制未修改的服务，
so if if I am able to replicate all these operations to different server instances of servers,
所以，如果我能够将所有这些操作复制到不同服务器实例，
then servers gets replicated freely without having to modify it at all,
然后服务器可以自由复制，根本不需要修改它，
so this is what we did,
这就是我们所做的，
when I worked on,
当我工作的时候，
I implemented chain replication based fault tolerance scheme,
我实现了基于链式复制的容错方案，
I use named is like a configuration,
我使用 named ，是一种配置服务，
and I replicated 2 different services without any modification
我复制了 2 个不同的服务，没有任何修改，
and in-memory file system and a service which exposes durable storage from a local machines
内存中文件系统（memfsd）
and so I'll quickly show them that.
所以我会很快地向展示它们。
So let's stop this,
所以让我停止这个，
let's see.
让我们看看。
So, for example I can,
所以，比如，我可以，
so I can start up a bunch of replicates,
所以我可以开始一系列的复制，
so if I look into the 9P name space module in Linux,
所以，如果我看一下 Linux 中的 9P 名称空间模块，
you see this memfs-replica,
你可以看到这个 memfs-replica ，
here's where these replicas register themselves,
这是这些复制注册它们自己的地方，
so we can see that, we have five of these replicas up,
所以我们可以看到，
I can write to one of them.
我可以写入它们中的一个。
Oops.
糟糕。
Okay, so can I write to one of the replicas
好的，我可以写入复制中的一个，
and then I can read from another one group,
然后我可以从另一组中读取，
because we should get the same result outside wrote,
因为我们应该得到相同的结果，
you can read from the last replica,
你可以从最后一个副本中读取，
should get the same thing back,
应该能获得相同的东西，
can even crash replica, because,
甚至可以使副本崩溃，因为，
so let's kill one of these guys,
所以，让我们杀死其中一个，
we can see this,
我们可以看到，
see there are only four replicas left now in the name space,
现在名字空间里只剩下四个副本了，
then write a different string to this file,
然后向这个文件写入不同的字符串，
and, I should,
而且，我应该，
yeah, so, so now, despite a failure,
是的，所以，所以现在，尽管一个失败了，
the service automatically reconfigured,
服务自动重新配置，
and the in-memory file systems services based off,
以及基于的内存中文件系统服务，
did not have to be modified at all,
根本不需要修改，
you can just plug in any new service you want to,
你只需插入任何你想要的新服务，
that implements this 9P interface
实现 9P 接口的，
and it should work out of the box.
而且它应该开箱即用。
So, I think that's,
所以，我认为这是，
I think that sort of concludes my presentation
我想我的演示到此结束了，
and I'd be happy to take any more questions,
我很乐意回答更多的问题，
you guys might have.
你们可能有的。
I regret not wearing my Plan9 shirt this time,
我后悔这次没有穿我的 Plan9 衣服，
I should have,
我应该这么做的，
I'm curious though, I'm working on something that was sort of similar earlier this semester,
不过我很好奇，
except there was no replication,
只是没有复制，
it was just 9P services under Linux box,
它只是 Linux 机器下的 9P 服务，
why this is sort of an offhand question, why change replication,
为什么，这是一个即兴的问题，
I imagine there are other replication schemes,
我想还有其他的复制方案，
that are available for this sort of thing,
在这类事情上是可用的，
and in theory because this is 9P,
从理论上讲，因为这是 9P ，
you could probably bind all these replicas over the same space,
你可能会把所有这些副本都绑定在同一个命名空间，
they look like, it's a machine,
它们看起来像是一台机器，
but why chain replication.
但为什么是链式复制？
Yeah, yeah, good question,
是的，是的，好问题，
you could in theory do any any replication scheme you'd like, under the hood,
理论上，你可以做任何你想做的复制方案，
I did chain application, because it seemed like a simple starting point, I guess,
我做了链式复制，
I could also throw this on top of a raft interpretation,
我也可以把这个放在 Raft 实现上，
like the entry class or anything like that,
比如条目或类似的东西，
it's something fundamental about the choice.
这是关于选择的一些基本问题。
Does your system support adding additional replicas after it started.
你的系统是否支持在启动后添加其他副本？
Yeah, great question,
是的，好问题，
so you already know that's a work in progress,
所以你已经知道，这是一项正在进行的工作，
but yeah currently we don't support adding additional replicas out of box.
但是，是的，目前我们不支持添加额外的副本。
This is an open question,
这是一个开放的问题，
it's sort of like you may not know this,
比如你可能不知道这个，
this wasn't the express intent of the purpose,
这不是目的的明确意图，
but one of the things that's really cool about Plan9 and 9P is that,
但 Plan9 和 9P 真正酷的一点是，
you treat network connections like their files as well,
你也将网络连接视为它们的文件，
so you're like you have like memfs, you have from what I saw a scheduler queue was implemented,
所以你有 memfs ，
just set of files,
只是一些文件，
do you and this is an open question,
你是否，这是一个开放的问题，
because the question of whether network stuff over file interfaces,
因为文件接口上的网络是否存在问题，
scalable is difficult to answer,
可伸缩性很难回答，
but do you also implement this in sort of that way
但你是否也以这种方式实现这一点，
or do you use more traditional policy interfaces to,
或者你是否使用更传统的[]接口，
when the clients use this thing they presume they use traditional sockets and things to communicate.
当客户端使用这个东西时，
Yeah, yeah, good question,
是的，是的，好问题，
so yeah, everything, so all the clients and services communicate over TCP at the moment,
所以，是的，所有的东西，
and yeah it is a good question
是的，这是一个很好的问题，
as to whether the 9P spaces actually performed enough
9P 命名空间是否性能足够好，
for what we're gonna do with it,
我们要用它来做什么，
as far as we can see now,
就我们现在所能看到的，
there's not,
没有，
so we've done some performance benchmarking
所以我们做了一些性能基准测试，
to see how well like we've written a scheduler over 9P,
来了解我们在 9P 上编写的调度器有多好，
and we've done some performance benchmarking to see how it performs
我们已经做了一些性能基准测试，看看它的表现如何，
and it seems to not add a ton of overhead at the moment,
目前它似乎并没有增加太多的开销，
but, alright, we can imagine those trade-offs changing for different types of services
但是，我们可以想象不同类型的服务的权衡会发生变化，
and as the scheduler becomes more or less oversubscribed.
并且调度器或多或少变得超额订阅。
I guess, I guess to clarify,
我想澄清一下，
so sorry I'm taking up taking up a lot of time,
很抱歉我占用了你很多时间，
but just briefly the whole 9P,
但只是简单地说，整个 9P ，
if you if you were able to
如果你如果你能够，
and this is again very open,
这也是非常开放的，
but if you were able to treat network connections files, you have replicas, right,
但如果你能够把网络连接当成文件，
you could have something for each card,
你可以为每一个网卡准备一些东西，
then shared network traffic over those network cards,
然后在这些网卡上分片网络流量，
which I guess this is serverless anyway,
我想这是无服务器的，
so it probably doesn't make that much of a difference,
所以这可能不会有太大不同，
yeah, forget it,
是的，算了，
because you already have the handles for you.
因为你已经有自己的处理了。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Alright, so let's hear about some verification stuff, if you're ready.
好的，让我们来听一些关于验证的东西，如果你准备好了。
Can you guys hear me, okay.
你们能听到我说话吗？
Yes.
是的。
Alright, excellent,
好的，太好了，
so indeed, I'm gonna talk to you about my project,
所以，我要和你们谈谈我的项目，
which is focused on modular verification for distributed systems,
它专注于分布式系统的模块化验证。
so let's start by answering the obvious question,
所以让我们从回答这个显而易见的问题开始，
which is why bother with any of this stuff,
为什么关心这个东西，
and I think anyone that's worked in the lab for 6.824
我认为任何完成 6.824 实验的人，
must have discovered at some point,
一定是在某个时候发现，
that getting this resistance right is hard,
让这种[]变得正确是困难的，
there's a lot of non determinism caused by concurrency and network failure,
并发和网络故障导致了大量的不确定性，
and that makes it very difficult to exhaust the test
这使得测试变得非常困难，
to make sure there's no corner case bugs,
为了确保没有边界 bug ，
verification is an alternative to, alternative approach testing to try and get correctness
验证是获得正确性的另一种方法测试，
and in principle, it can entirely rule out bugs,
理论上，它可以完全排除 bug ，
with verification you've basically mathematically modeled your system
通过验证，你已经对系统进行了数学建模，
and improve some theorem about that model,
并改进了关于该模型的一些定理，
and you know one of the downsides of verification is that,
验证的一个缺点是，
it's quite a lot of work during these formal proofs is
需要做相当多的工作，
by no means easy
绝非易事，
and even if it was easy, verification still wouldn't be a perfect silver bullet,
即使这很容易，
for one verification, you have to make sure that you get your specification right,
对于一个验证，你必须确保你的规格是正确的，
if the mathematical theorem you're proving by your system
如果你用你的系统证明的数学定理
doesn't actually say what you really wanted to say,
并没有说出你真正想说的，
then what you've proved is useless
那么你所证明的一切都是无用的，
and relatedly, you have to make sure that the model that you have to resist them is also complete,
与之相关的是，
if you fail to model some execution that can happen in reality,
如果你不能对现实中可能发生的一些执行进行建模，
but you don't consider, then your theorem would apply to the real world.
但你不考虑，
And some of you that are familiar with some distributed verification work,
你们中的一些人熟悉一些分布式验证工作，
might say well don't we already know how to do this,
可能会说，我们不是已经知道怎么做了吗，
indeed distributed systems have always been hard
事实上，分布式系统一直很难实现，
and people have recently worked on a project to try to verify actual implementations of distributed systems,
人们最近致力于一个项目，
so some of these projects include IronFleet and Verdi,
其中一些项目包括 IronFleet 和 Verdi ，
however, these projects didn't focus much on modularity
然而，这些项目并没有太多地关注模块化，
or trying to prove reusable specifications for components of systems,
或者试图证明系统组件的可重用规范，
trying to build more complicated systems out of them,
试图用它们来建造更复杂的系统，
and I'd argue that that's the way that distributed systems are actually built,
我认为这就是分布式系统的实际构建方式，
the way you build a distributed system is by
构建分布式系统的方法是通过
oftentimes using building blocks,
通常使用构建块，
like kv values services and lock services or or zookeeper
比如键值服务、锁服务或 Zookeeper ，
and putting them together with some you know added code and novel functionality
将它们放在一起，
to build your more interesting and more useful system,
为了建立更有趣、更有用的系统，
and are sort of thesis if you will,
这是一种论题，
is that verification can and should exploit this compositionality,
验证可以而且应该利用这种构成性，
as one sort of targeted goal,
作为一种有针对性的目标，
we aim to prove specifications for client systems,
我们的目标是证明客户端系统的规格，
firework like IronFleet Verdi simply reason about what the behavior of the actual server side [] looks like,
之前的工作，比如 IronFleet Verdi 简单地推理，
and don't explicitly model or prove anything about what the client programs actually do
没有显式地建模
and oftentimes there's a bit of logic on the client,
而且通常情况下，客户端上有一些逻辑，
that's crucial for getting correctness,
这对于获得正确的结果至关重要，
and the approach we use is to use advances in concurrent separation logic,
我们使用的方法是
which is a compositional means of reasoning about concurrent programs,
它是关于并发程序的推理的组合手段，
that's lately become popular for popular
它最近变得流行起来，
and demonstrate to be successful at raising about real code.
证明成功地提出了关于推理真正的代码。
So the first example that we worked on,
所以我们研究的第一个例子，
was verifying a sharded value system,
是验证一个分片的键值系统，
the keys in this are a statically split up into shards
其中的键是静态分成不同的分片，
and shards themselves can be moved between the shard servers,
并且分片本身可以在分片服务器之间移动，
so it's very similar to lab 4 of of 6.824,
它与 6.824 的实验 4 非常相似，
except that it's not replicated,
只是它不是复制的，
so there's no there's no raft in this,
所以这里面没有 Raft ，
and, it's purely in memory.
而且，它纯粹是在内存中。
Besides that, our system also has shared servers and a coordinator server
除此之外，我们的系统还具有分片服务器和协调服务器，
and the coordinator is the one that tells other shard servers
协调器是通知其他分片服务器，
to move shard between themselves
在分片之间移动，
as you nodes want to join
在想加入或需要重新平衡时，
the top of a library that we provide
我们提供的高级别的库，
and that we want to prove specification for is you know we call it a KVClerk,
我们想要证明的规范是，
which is a client object that one can use
它是一个用户可以使用的客户端对象，
and we call these three functions on to actually interact with the server,
我们调用这三个函数
so there's a Put, you you say what value to Put in,
有一个 Put ，你要把什么值放入键中，
and then there's a conditionalPut,
然后有一个 ConditionalPut ，
which will only put the new value, if the old value is the expected one,
它只会放入新值，如果旧值是期望值，
and we aim to basically implement a implement a linearizable key value service
我们的目标是实现一个可线性化的键值服务，
and approve a classification that shows linearizable
并批准规范，显示可线性化，
and the way you do this in the separation logic style
你执行这个，使用分离逻辑方式，
is basically by writing a specification that look a lot like this,
是通过编写一个看起来很像这样的规范，
so this basically says that if the object ck is a key value clerk,
这基本上是说，如果对象 ck 是一个 KVClerk ，
then you have specifications for the put and get functions,
然后你就有了 Put 和 Get 函数的规范，
that say for example, if you start running the put function,
例如，如果你开始运行 Put 函数，
with the precondition that key k has value w,
在键 k 具有值 w 的前提下，
then by the end of it,
然后在它结束时，键 k 是值 v ，
similarly, if you do a get
同样，如果你执行一个 Get ，
and you know that a key k has value v at the beginning,
键 k 在开始时的值是 v ，
then that's the thing that's going to be returned
那么这就是要返回的东西，
and you're still going to know that's the value of the key,
你仍然会知道这就是键的值，
although the specifications look pretty simple
尽管这些规范看起来很简单，
and you might think, of course the key value service does
您可能会想，键值服务当然会，
and that's sort of the point that these top level client specifications are as simple as they can be
这就是关键，
and and basically hide all the details of the fact,
并且隐藏了事实的所有细节，
that there's multiple shard servers
有多个分片服务器，
and that this clerk library might need to talk to servers multiple times,
这个 Clerk 库可能需要与服务器多次交互，
it might need to refresh its information about which server owns the,
它可能需要刷新它的信息，
and we basically you prove respect that allows you to forget all that
我们基本上证明了，让你忘记这一切，
and use a key guy service just by calling these puts and gets
使用键值服务，只需要调用 Put 和 Get ，
and having this idealized notion of what the key value mapping actually looks like.
有了这个理想化的概念，
So I won't talk too much more in detail about what the actual proof looks like,
所以我不会太详细地谈论
instead to focus to, issue focus towards a next thing we were interested in doing,
相反，要把重点放在，
which is actually doing something with a bit of fault tolerance to this,
做一些容错性的事情。
so I can mention the key value itself is not replicated
所以如我所说，键值本身不是复制的，
and isn't fault tolerant
并且不能容错，
and so we started by trying to figure out how to verify the simplest possible fault tolerant protocol,
所以，我们开始尝试找出
and we basically started a Single-decree Paxos
我们从单决议 Paxos 开始，
to decree paxos is a classic protocol for getting contents on a single value,
单决议 Paxos 是用于在单个值获取共识的经典协议，
so whereas with a raft,
与 Raft 相比，
you can get you replicate entire log
你可以复制整个日志，
and you keep appending new entries to log,
你不停地在日志中添加新的条目，
single-decree paxos is the [] of multi []
单决议 Paxos 是多 Paxos 的[]，
and basically functions of write once register,
基本上一次写入寄存器的功能，
if you want to set the value to something,
如果要将值设置为某个值，
you can attempt to write to it,
你可以尝试对其进行写入，
and if someone else beat you,
如果有人打败了你，
then, that's too bad for you,
那对你来说太糟糕了，
and now the value has already been decided
现在值已经确定了，
and it's never going to change again,
它再也不会改变了。
so we implemented and partially verified a single-decree paxos implementation
所以，我们实现并部分验证了单决议 Paxos 实现，
and basically prove a specification that shows that it's a write once register
证明了它是一次写入寄存器的规范，
and the key idea in the specification and the proof
规范和证明中的关键思想是，
you get irrevocable knowledge of what that a committed value is
你得到了不可撤销的知识关于提交的值是什么，
and you basically know that from here on out,
你知道，从现在开始，
if anybody else ever sees any committed value,
如果其他人看到任何提交的值，
it's going to be the exact same thing that you see right now.
这将是你现在看到的完全相同的东西。
And thinking about this a little bit after we worked on the proof of it,
在我们研究了它的证明之后，考虑这个问题，
we sort of thinking that,
我们想到，
we sort of notice that,
我们注意到，
there's a slight generalization you can do to single-decree paxos,
你可以对单决议 Paxos 做一个轻微的概括，
which a we all Monotone Paxos for lack of better name
我们称为单调的 Paxos ，因为没有更好的名字，
and the idea is rather than gaining knowledge about the exact value upon a commit,
这个想法是，
you instead can we modify the protocol,
我们可以修改协议，
so that you only gain knowledge about a lower bound on the value,
这样你就只能获得关于值的下界的知识，
so, basically when you commit a value,
所以，当你提交一个值时，
for example you commit at number 15 to this write, once register
例如，你提交数字 15 到这个写入一次寄存器，
rather than knowing that 15 is the only value to anybody else in the future, we're going to see,
不是知道 15 是唯一的值，
you'll know that any value that people see in the future
人们在未来看到的任何值，
as committed is going to be at least 15,
提交的至少是 15 ，
and so of course doing this requires having some notion of what larger than actually means for the value type.
当然，要做到这一点，需要一些概念，
And the key idea is a replica can always find out what the latest committed value is
关键思想是
and choose to increase it
并选择增加它，
and other replicates can continually find out larger and larger lower bounds on basically the value so far is,
而其他副本可以不断地找出
and once we sort of came up with this idea of monotone paxos,
一旦我们想出了单调 Paxos 的想法，
we realized immediately that we can do log replication with this,
我们立刻意识到，
so the set of values V, we can choose to simply be all the logs,
所以这组值 V ，
that you might want to replicate your logs of operations
你可能希望复制你的操作日志，
and we can define one log to be bigger than another one,
我们可以定义一个日志大于另一个，
if the smaller one is a prefix of l1 is a prefix of l2,
如果较小的是，如果 l1 是 l2 的前缀，
and this basically allows us to know,
这让我们知道，
this sort of yield a protocol which you'll have to trust,
这就产生了一种你必须信任的协议，
that I'm showing you the code for,
我现在给你们看的代码，
in which you can gain information about what the prefix of the log is
你可以在其中获取有关日志前缀的信息，
and over time you can add new things to log
随着时间的推移，你可以向日志中添加新的内容，
by making it larger and larger
通过让它变得越来越大，
and that's pretty much exactly what we mean,
这几乎就是我们的意思，
when we say log replication.
当我们说到日志复制时。
The problem with this exact protocol is that
这个协议的问题是，
naively if we implement the most naive version of this monotone paxos thing,
我们实现了单调 Paxos 最幼稚的版本，
you would need to send around the full log on every single RPC,
你需要在每个 RPC 上发送完整的日志，
in single-decree paxos, those you sent around the [fault] value on all the RPCs
在单决议 Paxos 中，
and the new trivial generalization of the model in paxos would have to be sent around the full log,
在 Paxos 中的微不足道的概括
that's not really useful to log to get larger and larger and larger
这并不是真正有用的，日志变得越来越大，
and the beginning of log is no longer relevant by the time,
并且日志开始时，与时间无关，
everybody agreed to commit
每个人都同意提交，
and all that, so you could try to optimize this by only passing around a suffix of the log
所有这些，
and indeed, there's a whole sequence of optimization,
事实上，有一个完整的优化序列，
you can make to this monotone paxos based log replication,
你可以对这种基于单调 Paxos 的日志进行复制，
and as you start doing more and more of this,
当你开始做越来越多这样的事情时，
you'll realize that this looks exactly like raft
你会意识到这看起来和 Raft 很像。
and in fact, We aimed basically to use our idea of monitoring paxos
事实上，我们的目标是利用我们的 Monotone Paxos ，
not to implement a new replication protocol,
不是实现新的复制协议，
but rather to a verify a raft like system,
而是验证一个类似 Raft 的系统，
so we have this proof for single-decree paxos,
所以我们有这个单决议 Paxos 的证明，
we have this clear generalization to this monotone paxos thing
我们对这种单调 Paxos 有一个明确的概括，
and our hope is that we can use the idea of monotone paxos,
我们的希望是，我们可以利用单调 Paxos 想法，
so to basically verify raft directly,
直接验证 Raft ，
as opposed to rely on the much more complicated correctness argued for raft,
不同于依赖 Raft 的更为复杂的正确性争论，
that has been described in sort of other state machine type styles.
已经在某种其他状态机类型的样式中进行了描述。
So this is our future work,
所以这是我们未来的工作，
and the key takeaway I I sort of want to leave you guys with is that
我想告诉你们的关键一点是，
reasoning both formal and informal about distributed systems,
关于分布式系统的正式和非正式推理，
should be as compositional as writing code,
应该像编写代码一样进行组合，
the way you scale writing code is modular,
编写代码的扩展方式是模块化的，
and that's the way reasoning should also scale.
这就是推理也应该进行扩展的方式。
And that's all for my presentation,
我的演讲到此结束，
I'm happy to take questions.
我很乐意回答大家的提问。
If the answer is too long,
如果答案太长，
you can look me in the chat,
你可以在聊天中看到我，
but I was curious,
但我很好奇，
I know there's a closet,
我知道有个[]，
do you have any resources for somebody interested in getting into as a from a software perspective,
你有没有什么资源，
like any brief recommendations.
任何简短的建议。
Are you, so yeah, I guess I'm not quite sure what the,
你是，所以，是的，我想我不是很确定，
so, are you interested in like,
那么，你有没有兴趣，
I I should message afterward,
我应该在之后发消息，
but if you're interested I guess,
但如果你感兴趣的话，
in a sort most lightweight versions of verification,
我想，在某种最轻量级的验证版本中，
I think [Daphne] is a great tool to learn,
我认为 Dafny 是一个很好的学习工具，
because it's a pretty simple starting point,
因为这是一个非常简单的起点，
you can write real code and get a feel for things,
你可以编写真正的代码，并对事物有感觉，
I think a lot of a lot of verification is pretty academic
我认为很多的验证都是相当学术的，
and not super close to being really useful at verification like this,
在像这样的验证中并不是非常有用，
so I'm not sure how useful it really would be for,
所以我不确定它到底有多大用处，
real software during just yet,
真正的软件目前还没有，
so the hope is that one day it will be.
所以，人们希望有一天它会成为现实。
Thanks.
谢谢。
Did you implement this version of paxos you're talking about.
你有没有实现你所说的这个版本的 Paxos ？
This monotone paxos those thing.
这个单调 Paxos 东西。
So, yeah I implemented rather than implementing a generic monotone paxos thing,
所以，是的，我实现了，
which wouldn't really make sense
这没有意义，
so in this monotone monotone log application thing,
所以，在单调日志应用程序中，
all the RPC center on the full log,
所有 RPC 发送整个日志，
if you run it for a long time to get way too slow,
如果你运行了很长时间变得太慢，
because the RPCs are sending too much stuff,
因为 RPC 发送了太多的东西，
but yeah I did implement it,
是的，我确实实现了，
and I think we're working on actually trying to reason about it.
我认为我们正在努力试图对它进行推理。
Did you [vanish] to figure out how performing it actually ends up being
你有没有[]弄清楚它的性能，
or how it works in practice.
或者它在实践中是如何运作的？
So I think the exact code that we have right now is not code you'd want to run
所以我认为我们现在所拥有的代码并不是你想要运行的代码，
and my, in a sense, it ought to be as performant as raft,
而我的，
sort of is and we don't really have an optimized implementation,
我们并没有真正优化的实现，
so I haven't actually bothered getting performance numbers for it at all,
我根本没有去获取它的性能数据，
it's probably pretty slow, not really sure.
它可能相当慢，不是很确定。
Great, thank you,
好的，谢谢，
yeah, even if we verify my programs,
是的，即使我们验证了我的程序，
I'm sure on this lock somewhere,
我肯定日志在某个地方，
but let's hear from PP2 now.
但现在让我们来听听 PP2 。
Alright, can everyone see?
好的，大家都能看到吗？
Great.
好的。
So, we are the [pigeon] protocol team, me [] me Jay Timmy,
我们是[]协议团队，我， Jay 和 Timmy ，
and we are we present a simple distributed file system,
我们展示一个简单的分布式文件系统，
and the reason we selected a distributed file system
我们选择分布式文件系统的原因是，
is that users often times want to sort data privately in a really accessible way
用户经常希望对数据进行私有排序，
without the implications of using a cloud company,
在使用云公司的影响，
where you don't own your own data.
你不拥有你自己的数据。
So we wanted to create a solution,
所以我们想要创造一个解决方案，
where you self host, your data in a fault tolerant distributed manner on commodity hardware,
你托管自己的数据
and our file system is really similar to Frangipani,
我们的文件系统非常类似于 Frangipani ，
except that it uses raft instead of pedal
除了它使用 Raft 而不是 Petal ，
and the file system is on the servers instead of the clients.
并且文件系统在服务器上，而不是客户端上。
In terms of file system parameters,
在文件系统参数方面，
we also have a 4096 byte block size
我们还有一个 4096 字节的数据块大小，
and a 2 megabyte maximum file size,
和 2M 字节的最大文件大小，
we theoretically have a 32 gigabyte maximum disk capacity,
理论上我们有 32G 的最大磁盘容量，
however this is actually constrained by your RAM,
然而，这受到你的 RAM 的限制，
so if you only have 8 gigabyte of RAM,
如果你只有 8G 的 RAM ，
you would have, however much left over after your, after whatever your system takes up.
你会有，
And we support as many servers and clients as we can within reason,
我们在合理范围内支持尽可能多的服务器和客户端，
obviously the more servers and clients that you add to the locking contention,
显然，你向锁争用中添加的服务器和客户端越多，
there will be less performance as you start to access the same file over and over again.
性能将会降低，
And, in terms of performance,
就性能而言，
well, we were very heavily focused on availability and crash recovery,
我们非常关注可用性和崩溃恢复，
so we didn't, we didn't measure performance
我们没有测量性能，
and we think it's probably pretty bad,
我们认为情况可能相当糟糕，
because our system is built on top of raft,
因为我们的系统是建立在 Raft 上的，
which is not known to be the most performance of systems.
这并不是已知的系统中性能最好的。
So, over to Jay.
所以，轮到 Jay 了。
So, again performance is not the biggest thing that we have,
所以，再说一次，性能不是我们最重要的东西，
but we do have very very strong consistency guarantees,
但我们确实有非常强大的一致性保证，
in particular we enforce POSIX consistency,
特别是，我们强制执行 POSIX 一致性，
which is a form of strong consistency,
这是一种强一致性的形式，
we usually see on local file systems,
我们通常在本地文件系统上看到，
so we enforce the invariant that after a file,
所以我们强制了不变量，
any read of your previously written bytes from anywhere,
从任何地方读取你之前写入的字节，
or will turn the data specified by that previous write,
将返回之前写入的数据，
similarly any new writes over that data will result in visible overwrites of that data,
类似地，对该数据的任何新写入
from the perspective of other readers.
从其他读取者的角度来看。
So in order to achieve this,
所以，为了实现这个，
we have a data mode journal that is built into this sort of block layer,
我们有一个数据模式日志，
that is again distributed with raft and replicated
它是 Raft 分布式的并复制，
and which is effectively a write-ahead log,
实际上是预写日志，
that guarantees the atomicity of writes strong semantics in the presence of crashes,
保证了在存在崩溃的情况下强语义的写入原子性，
the same as raft pretty much
和 Raft 差不多，
and also the consistency model that we offer above.
以及我们上面提供的一致性模型。
So servers also in order to help with this,
所以，服务器也为了帮助实现这一点，
we issue distributed locking, so we can have this very primitive block cache,
我们发布分布式锁，
as you would see in a local file system,
正如你在本地文件系统中看到的，
and also we have, we've leases to make sure that there's mutually exclusive access to all of these blocks.
我们也有租约，
Right, so to allow our clients to use our file system,
所以为了允许我们的客户端使用我们的文件系统，
we created a POSIX like interface,
我们创建了一个类 POSIX 的接口，
where users can interact with files,
用户可以与文件交互，
we mainly have four functions open, close, read, write,
我们主要四个函数， Open Close Read Write ，
open and close are pretty explanatory,
Open 和 Close 很容易解释，
they just open and close file descriptors on our file system,
它们只是打开和关闭我们文件系统上的文件描述符，
read, it just takes a file descriptor
Read ，它只需要一个文件描述符，
and read a fixed number of bytes at the current file position,
并在当前文件位置读取固定数量的字节，
write also takes a file descriptor and read flush is,
Write 也获取文件描述符，并且读刷新是，
sorry write takes a file descriptor
抱歉， Write 操作需要文件描述符，
and just writes the data to the file [],
并将数据写入文件，
but it's in a different way than a normal POSIX write,
但它的方式与正常的 POSIX 写入方式不同，
because instead flushes the buffer copy of the file,
因为不是刷新文件的缓冲复制，
and then appends the new data on this,
然后在上面追加新的数据，
so instead of a normal POSIX write,
所以，与正常的 POSIX 写入不同，
where we just write to a [] descriptor with a buffer
我们只需使用缓冲区写入文件描述符，
and the number of bytes to write it does, what I just said instead.
而要写入的字节数，正如我刚才所说的那样。
And we have a demo to represent clients interacting with the system.
我们有一个演示来演示客户端与系统的交互。
So this is just a quick demonstration of our file system
所以，这是我们的文件系统的快速演示，
being run both serially and concurrently,
在串行和并行运行的情况下，
so what's going to happen is console one
在控制台一中发生的是，
or I should say left console
或者我应该说左控制台，
is going to open up a file called tt, just testing thing,
将打开一个名为 tt 的文件，只是测试一下，
it's going to write something to the file,
它会在文件中写入一些内容，
and then the console on the right is going to read from it afterwards,
然后右边的控制台随后将读取它，
per the consistency model,
根据一致性模型，
they should see the same thing as the left console wrote
它们应该看到与左侧控制台所写的相同的内容，
and indeed after a minute, we see that.
事实上，一分钟后，我们就看到了这个。
Okay, so the next thing that's going to happen is,
好的，接下来会发生的事情是，
both console one and console two are going to try to flush their local copies of this file at the same time,
控制台一和控制台而都将尝试
this is not a traditional POSIX write,
这不是传统的 POSIX 写入，
they're both taking the copies of the file that they have
它们都有它们拥有的文件的复制，
and trying to put them onto disk at the same time,
并试图同时将它们放到磁盘上，
so it's sort of like two writes from offset zero,
所以从偏移量零开始的两次写入，
one of these is going to win,
其中一个会赢，
and we can look at the log on the left console,
我们可以查看左侧控制台上的日志，
as it commits
因为它提交，
and actually see, after a moment,
过一会儿，你会看到，
that both transactions run concurrently,
两个事务同时运行，
they both take up different parts of the log,
它们都占据了日志的不同部分，
but at the end of the day,
但归根结底，
the left console transaction is going to win,
左侧控制台事务将获胜，
so it was completely atomic everything works.
所以，它完全是原子的，一切都是有效的。
So this.
所以，这是。
I think you got muted.
我想你被静音了。
Sorry, I muted,
抱歉，我静音了，
due to time there are more,
由于时间的原因，还有更多的，
there are some limitations and features we can add to our file system,
我们可以向我们的文件系统添加一些限制和功能，
so firstly, we only have one root directory,
首先，我们只有一个根目录，
so adding more will definitely be a plus,
所以增加更多肯定会是一个加分，
next we only, should persist blocks to disk rather than RAM,
接下来，我们只是，
because that's what we're currently doing,
因为这就是我们目前正在做的事情，
but we should also consider that what we're doing,
但我们也应该考虑到我们正在做的事情，
has a lot of writes,
有很多写入，
so it could be pretty bad,
所以情况可能会很糟糕，
if we just keep writing,
如果我们继续写下去，
doing have a lot of writes for just one operation,
一次操作就有大量写入，
we also only have direct inode blocks rather than having direct and indirect inodes,
我们也只有直接 inode 块，
so that would be a plus to add those,
所以这将是一个加号，
and secondly, there should be a better way for clients to interact with this file system,
其次，
so there could be a fuse layer
所以可能有一个 FUSE 层，
or they could just be better positive compliance in general.
或者，它们可能是更好的 POSIX 兼容。
Concludes our presentation.
我们的演讲结束了。
Do you want to talk a little bit about how you tested this?
你想谈谈你是如何测试这个的吗？
Sure, so we had a pretty at your [recommendation],
当然，所以我们有一个，在你的推荐下，
we had a pretty broad set of tests,
我们有一套相当广泛的测试，
we had so to begin each component,
开始每个组件，
so each you know the block layer right here,
所以每个块层，
individual raft key values,
单独的 Raft 键值，
we had the journal
我们有日志，
and we had all these things,
我们有所有这些东西，
we basically mocked every layer underneath,
我们 mock 了下面的每一层，
each layer we were testing and tested
我们测试的每一层，
did sort of unit testing,
做了一些单元测试，
you can't really call it unit testing, once you get high enough,
你不能把它叫做单元测试，一旦你达到了足够高的程度，
because you're so reliant on lower layers being correct,
因为你太依赖较低层次的正确性，
but we did as best we could,
但我们尽了最大努力，
from there we did integration testing
从那里我们进行了集成测试，
and you know wrote out a set of partitions,
写出了一组分区，
one of those partitions is sort of what you just saw,
其中一个分区就是你刚才看到的，
the most interesting of them,
其中最有趣的是，
there were five of them,
这里有五个，
you can see them in our git repository,
你可以在我们的 Git 仓库中看到它们，
and then we also, to what degree, we could,
然后我们也，在多大程度上，我们可以，
so this didn't necessarily entirely work,
所以这并不一定完全奏效，
just because of some of the time limitations that we had,
因为我们有一些时间限制，
but we also attempted to do some stress testing,
但我们也试图做一些压力测试，
obviously performance numbers aren't great,
显然，性能数据并不是很好，
because it's not supposed to be great,
因为这不应该是很棒的，
but, the best we could,
但是，尽我们所能，
so we're pretty sure this is at least correct verified here.
因此，我们非常确定这至少是在这里得到证实的。
One interesting thing is that you're basically shooting for actually slightly stronger consistency property that POSIX are required,
一件有趣的事情是，
just two proceeds write into a single file,
两个进程写入到一个文件中，
there's actually not much,
实际上并没有太多，
actually the write [] we have to have to do.
写入，我们必须要做的。
Yes, that was kind of accidental,
是的，那是一种意外，
but we were,
但我们是，
so it's kind of stronger.
所以它更强了。
Yeah.
是的。
It was accidental, but it happened,
这是意外，但它确实发生了，
so we were like cool, it worked.
所以我们认为酷，它起作用了。
The server, I mean I think part of what sort of happened was,
服务器，我的意思是，我认为发生的一部分是，
that we guarantee we,
我们保证，
I positively guarantees I talked about,
我肯定我说过的话，
but we also make the guarantee that the block writes are all atomic,
但我们也保证块写入都是原子的，
and I think that's why we get this sort of stronger consistency,
我认为这就是为什么我们会得到这种更强的一致性，
because of the whole journal thing,
因为日志这件事，
yes, you could get your write overwritten,
是的，你可以让你的写入被覆盖，
if you do at the same time,
如果你同时这么做，
but it's always going to be clean.
但它总是[干净的]。
If you have aggressive caching,
如果你有主动缓存，
you might run in and don't write immediately to the log,
你可能会遇到，不立即写入日志，
then you might get different behavior.
那么你可能会得到不同的行为。
This is, why we don't aggressively cache,
这就是为什么我们不积极地缓存，
we have a block cache of size one.
我们有一个大小为 1 的数据块缓存。
Awesome, thank you, very cool,
太棒了，谢谢，很酷，
alright, our last group is presenting a game framework,
好的，我们的最后一组展示一个游戏框架，
whenever you're ready, take it away.
只要你准备好了，就可以开始。
Alright, so we're sure that many of you have played multiplayer games in quarantine,
好的，我们相信，
when you're bored.
当你无聊的时候。
So let's imagine that,
所以让我们想象一下，
you are a small indie game dev company
你是一家小型独立游戏开发公司，
and you're trying to develop a most player game,
你试图开发一款多玩家的游戏，
possibly that has either several different rooms,
可能有几个不同的房间，
something like chat penguin,
比如聊天企鹅，
where you might interact with other players in the same room,
你可能会和同一个房间里的其他玩家互动，
or perhaps it's like matchmaking base,
或者可能是匹配的情况，
where you're in a Lobby with several other players.
你和其他几个玩家在大厅里。
Well, so traditionally, how these work is that,
所以传统上，这些是如何工作的，
everything goes against process on one central server,
每件事都访问一台中央服务器上的进程，
but that central server is a bottleneck,
但中央服务器是一个瓶颈，
if every single player has to connect to that server to handle the game logic,
如果每个玩家都必须连接到那个服务器来处理游戏逻辑，
that server began a bottleneck by the number of requests that come through
那个服务器因通过的请求数量而开始出现瓶颈，
and also if that server goes down,
而且，如果服务器出现故障，
there goes your game.
这就是[]。
So what we're proposing is to create a distributed game framework,
所以，我们的计划是创建一个分布式游戏框架，
that instead, that's also fault tolerant,
这也是容错的，
so instead of having all the processing being on that central server,
所以，不是将所有处理都放在中央服务器上，
we actually distribute the game logic processing to several different worker servers,
我们将游戏逻辑处理分布到几个不同的工作服务器上，
but on top of that,
但最重要的是，
to be fault tolerant,
为了实现容错，
so when one of these worker servers goes down,
当这些工作服务器中的一个出现故障时，
we need to be able to handle that game logic
我们需要能够处理这种游戏逻辑，
and further move players to some other service workers,
并将玩家转移到其他一些工作服务器上，
so as part of that, we need to actually balance latency with fault tolerance,
所以，作为其中的一部分，
because if we make everything stay fault tolerant,
因为如果我们让一切保持容错，
we might run into a each move taking a long time to process.
我们可能会遇到，每个移动需要很长时间才能处理。
So that's why we're introducing Pinguino,
这就是为什么我们要介绍 Pinguino ，
which is our fault tolerant game framework,
这是我们的容错游戏框架，
that addresses all of the previous issues with distributed networks.
这解决了之前分布式网络的所有问题。
To dive a bit into the system of our framework,
为了深入了解我们框架的系统，
let's imagine the game club penguin,
让我们想象一下游戏俱乐部企鹅，
so in club penguin, user that is assigned into one room or one region,
在企鹅俱乐部，
it only really cares about talking and interacting with other users
它只关心与其他用户交谈和互动，
and the objects in that one room
以及那个房间里的物品，
and they don't really need to care about anything else that's happening in another room,
他们不需要关心
so there's no reason to have the request of every user be processed by one centralized servers,
所以，没有理由让
so instead we decided that we will have all of these requests be process across multiple workers,
所以，我们决定，
in order to do this, we have workers that are assigned to different regions,
为了做到这一点，
so if a player is in one region,
所以，如果玩家在一个地区，
they might be talking with the worker that is assigned to that region,
他们可能正在与分配到那个区域的 worker 交谈，
so for example in here,
例如，在这里，
the penguin that is in work,
企鹅在 worker 中，
that is assigned to the region for worker 2,
它被分配给区域的 worker 2 ，
we'll talk with worker 2 only,
我们只和 worker 2 交互，
but then the one in the worker and will talk with worker.
然后在 worker n 的会与 worker n 交互。
And additionally we mentioned,
此外，我们还提到，
we decided that this wouldn't the relation between worker and regions,
我们认为这不会影响 worker 和地区之间的关系，
doesn't necessarily have to be one to one mapping,
不一定是一对一的映射，
for some rooms that might be less popular and have less traffic,
对于一些可能不太受欢迎和流量较少的房间，
it's possible that a worker can handle multiple of those,
一个 worker 可能处理多个，
so there's that type of relation,
所以有这样一种关系，
that we need to keep track of.
我们需要追踪的。
And so in order to keep track of this,
所以，为了跟踪这一点，
we do need one centralized server,
我们确实需要一台中央服务器，
which is the coordinator,
这就是 coordinator ，
so the coordinator will be keeping track of all these mappings
所以， coordinator 将跟踪所有这些映射，
and some of the mapping includes the region to worker relation as well as region,
一些映射包括区域到 worker 的关系，
as well as the players itself,
以及玩家本身，
so for the fault tolerant aspect,
所处，在容错方面，
we have, that the workers will have two replicate each
我们有，每个 worker 有两个复制，
and surely we can talk a little bit more about what kind of information
[]将更多地谈论一下
And additionally, the coordinator,
另外， coordinator ，
because it is that one centralized server,
因为它是一台集中式服务器，
it is also a possible a failure point,
它也是一个可能的故障点，
so we have a coordinator backup
所以我们有一个 coordinator 备份，
and here the coordinator's main role is
这里 coordinator 的主要角色是，
just to keep track of all of these relations of the game states,
只是为了跟踪所有这些游戏状态的关系，
so information about the coordinator that changes for those relations
所以有关为这些关系更改的 coordinator 的信息
will be sent to the coordinator backup,
将被发送到 coordinator 备份，
before being processed a complete completely.
在处理完成之前。
So now with this, although we have that one server,
所以现在有了这个，虽然我们只有一台服务器，
the bulk of the traffic for games usually is
游戏的大部分流量通常是
players making moves and sending request process those moves
玩家进行移动并发送请求处理这些移动，
and those are now divided across multiple workers
这些被分配给多个 worker ，
and the coordinator is in charge of just a mapping
而 coordinator 负责映射，
and sending heartbeat to ensure that the workers are still alive
并发送心跳，以确保 worker 存活，
and can handle any failure cases.
可以处理任何故障情况。
Yep, so in the case that a worker goes down,
是的，所以在 worker 倒下的情况下，
we have the coordinator handling the reassignment of the players who were in that worker
我们让协调员来处理重新分配
and because the coordinator manages only the region mapping,
并且因为 coordinator 仅管理区域映射，
it's also easy for us to move around regions
对于我们来说，在不同地区之间移动也很容易
when one of us,
当比如一个 worker 超载时，
this allows us to perform some amount of load balancing,
这允许我们执行一定的负载平衡，
as we mentioned earlier.
正如我们之前提到的。
Cool, so I'll move on to what the developer API looks like,
酷，所以我将继续开发者 API 是什么样子的，
because another key feature that we wanted was
因为我们想要的另一个关键功能是，
for the framework to be easy to use,
为了使框架易于使用，
for a developer trying to code a new game in it,
对于试图在其中编写新游戏代码的开发人员来说，
so we treat the game as a state machine essentially
所以，我们将游戏视为一个状态机，
and so any move that the player makes,
所以玩家的任何移动，
actually fits into one of two different types of moves,
属于两种不同类型的动作之一，
so I mentioned earlier,
所以我之前提到过，
that we're trying to balance a bit of latency with fault tolerant,
我们试图在延迟和容错之间取得平衡，
so in order to provide a sort of choice for the developer,
所以为了给开发者提供一种选择，
we have two separate commands that we expose to the developer,
我们向开发人员开放了两个单独的命令，
the first is send fast move,
第一个是 sendFastMove ，
so this fast move make sure that the move gets to the replicas as soon as possible,
所以，这个快速移动确保
so the move gets processed as fast as possible on the worker,
以便在 worker 上尽可能快地处理移动，
on the other hand, we have sendStableMove,
另一方面，我们有 sendStableMove ，
which actually is a more fault tolerant move,
这是一个容错能力更强的移动，
that we expose to the developer
我们向开发人员公开的，
and this ensures this is mainly used for game critical logic changes,
这确保了，
such as say transaction,
例如交易，
so if you're buying something you don't want,
所以如果你要买什么东西，你不想，
like if you've already spent that money,
比如，如果你已经花了那笔钱，
you want to make sure that you get whatever you spend that money on your game
你想确保，
and so we guarantee that,
所以我们保证，
if that move gets fully processed and on the game,
如果移动得到完全处理，并在游戏中，
it's, it's stored on both of the replica,
它存储在两个副本上，
which ensures that if the worker that you're talking to goes down
这确保了如果与你交谈的 worker 倒下，
and the player gets transferred to a new worker,
然后玩家被转移到新的 worker 那里，
that new worker will be able to reconstruct the game,
新的 worker 将能够重建游戏，
including that transaction,
包括那笔交易，
this guarantee isn't done for a fast move,
这一保证不是为快速移动而做的，
which prioritizes the latency aspect,
对延迟方面进行了优先排序，
but you can also see here,
但你也可以在这里看到，
the move struct, that the developer defines are pretty general,
开发人员定义的 Move 结构非常通用，
so in the game that will be that we kind of developed as a toy demo for our framework,
所以，在游戏中，
it's kind of a chat penguin like interface.
这是一种聊天企鹅式的界面。
So each player is in several different rooms
所以每个玩家在几个不同的房间里，
and so within each room,
所以在每个房间里，
there's a chat window that you can talk to to interact with another player,
有一个聊天窗口，
so the two types of main moves,
所以两种主要的移动，
that you can make in this game
你可以在这个游戏中使用的是[]移动，
so a developer would just define like the X Y and the username of the player moving,
开发人员只需定义
and so the chat message is kind of the same words
所以 ChatMessage 是一种，
just like a chat message that you send into the window.
像你发送到窗口的聊天消息一样。
And so, we, in our game,
所以，在我们的游戏中，
we made chat messages a stable move
我们让聊天消息成为一个稳定的移动，
and move as a fast move,
像快速移动一样移动，
so even if like say one move gets dropped,
所以即使一个移动被放弃了，
it's okay,
也是可以的,
if you're a new kind of [teleports],
如果你是一种新的[]，
but, we don't want chat messages to randomly disappear,
但是，我们不希望聊天消息随机消失，
because they could be important messages.
因为它们可能是重要的信息。
So with that, I'll move on to the demo,
到此为止，我将继续演示，
which is a little bare bones,
这只是一个小的 demo ，
but should show off the functionality.
但应该展示一下它的功能。
So we have our super minimalist frontend,
所以我们有极简的前端，
and so when we move around the penguin,
所以当我们绕着企鹅走的时候，
we can see that, it's first sense of fast move,
我们可以看到，
and the replica that same move gets sent to the other replica
发送给另一个副本的相同的移动，
is assigned to the maine workers,
分配给主要的 worker ，
so right now, we're on worker zero,
所以现在，我们在 worker 0 ，
it gets replicated to work one and two,
它被复制成 worker 1 和 worker 2 ，
so we have two copies,
所以我们有两份复制，
and the game server then receives that change
然后游戏服务器接收那个改变，
and so they can process that locally,
这样它们就可以在本地处理这些信息，
and then if we send a chat message,
如果我们发送一条聊天消息，
we also have the player username
我们还有玩家用户名，
identified with the chat message sent,
用所发送的聊天消息标识，
but this is actually a stable move,
但这是一个稳定的移动，
so it's not visible in the logs,
所以它在日志中是不可见的，
but the stable moves wait until those moves are actually replicated to the workers
但稳定的移动要等到
and it's not easy to see here,
在这里看起来并不容易，
because normally there might be some amount of lag,
因为通常情况下可能会有一些滞后，
but when we do introduce some amount of lag into the network,
但当我们在网络中引入一定数量的滞后时，
that's move takes longer than it does,
那个移动要花更长的时间，
and now move it back to some future work that we want to implement.
现在移动到我们想要实现的一些未来工作中。
In terms of the backend,
在后台方面，
one additional thing that we would like to do
我们还想做一件事是，
is to allow the users to move across different rooms,
允许用户在不同的房间之间移动，
so right now, upon a user joining the game,
所以现在，当用户加入游戏时，
it'd be initialized,
它会被初始化，
they are assigned to one room,
他们被分配到一个房间，
but ideally if they want to move across to it,
但理想情况下，如果他们想要移动到那里去，
if they want to move to a different room,
如果他们想换个房间，
then they should be able to talk to the coordinator to be like,
然后他们应该能够与 coordinator 交互，
hey I'm gonna go to this region now,
嘿，我现在要去这个地区了，
can we load up the information of the game state from that region
你可以从那个区域加载游戏状态信息，
and then also now I'm going to start talking to a new worker.
然后，现在我要开始和一个新的 worker 交互。
And additionally we hinted at this earlier,
另外，我们早些时候也暗示过，
where we wanted to deal with region based worker load balancing,
我们希望处理基于区域的 worker 负载平衡，
so the reason why we had that,
所以我们拥有它的原因是，
why we did not go for one to one mapping with worker to region
为什么我们不采用 worker 到地区的一对一映射，
was to allow for this future work
是为了让这项未来的工作，
and we hope to be able to do that
我们希望能够做到这一点，
in order to control how much load each worker will be based with.
控制每个 worker 将承担多少负载。
Sorry, I have a question,
抱歉，我有个问题，
so are your,
所以，你的，
again, you have two actions sending a message and moving,
同样，你有两个动作来发送消息和移动，
so those actions are all atomic right,
所以，这些动作都是原子的，
are they like.
它们是不是。
Yeah.
是的。
They get sequentially processed
它们会被按顺序处理，
and since they are like individual moves,
因为它们是单独的移动，
they most of the time they only modify some variables
大多数情况下，他们只修改一些变量，
and they acquire that locks on those variables before the moves.
它们在移动之前对这些变量加锁。
So you said earlier, that you have a coordinator and coordinator backup
所以你之前说过，
and the replicas can talk to either of them,
副本可以与它们中的任何一个交互，
what happens if you have a network partition,
如果你有一个网络分区，
that separates the coordinator
分开 coordinator 和一些副本，
So the coordinator backup in case of a network partition,
所以 coordinator 备份，在网络分区的情况下，
the workers will be kind of lost,
worker 会丢失 coordinator ，
they'll only be able to talk to the coordinator
它们只能与 coordinator 交互，
and if a coordinator goes down,
如果 coordinator 倒下了，
then the backup gets brought up to actually start processing,
然后备份被启动开始处理，
so in that case of network partition,
所以，在网络分区情况下，
I don't think we will be like.
我不认为我们会。
The workers that are isolated and away from that coordinator
与 coordinator 分开的 worker
will not be able to be processed
将无法处理，
with the like the coordinator itself
与协调者本身，
and turns out the user side,
结果发现在用户端，
it can still be processed,
它仍然可以被处理，
because the player just needs to continue talking to that worker,
因为玩家只需要继续与那个 worker 交互，
it's just that, if there's any changes in the region,
如果这个区域有任何变化，
like the state of the game as a whole,
比如整个游戏的状态，
that will be processed yet.
它还会被处理。
Yeah, additionally I want to make that,
是的，另外我还想确认一下，
if we have a partition,
如果我们有一个分区，
the coordinator backup essentially acts as a coordinator
coordinator 备份作为一个 coordinator ，
for all of the workers that it can talk to
对于它可以交互的所有 worker ，
and this is fine,
这很好，
because we want the game to be still running for all of the regions
因为我们希望游戏仍然在所有地区运行，
in the workers at the coordinator backup is talking to,
在 coordinator 备份正在交互的 worker 中，
this mainly becomes a problem,
这主要成了一个问题，
when they do reunite
当它们重聚的时候，
and in this case the coordinator backup then takes all of its data
在这种情况下， coordinator 备份获取其所有数据，
and it can send it to the coordinator
并且它可以将其发送给 coordinator ，
and the coordinator can locally resolve it,
coordinator 可以本地解决该问题，
because there is kind of an original coordinator and the coordinator backup
因为有一种原始 coordinator 和 coordinator 备份，
and they know that the backup was, backup of the coordinator,
它们知道 coordinator 备份，
because it's stored locally.
因为它是本地储存的。
But if the coordinator backup becomes a coordinator,
但是如果 coordinator 备份称为 coordinator ，
then wouldn't it,
那不是，
for example say, oh I need to make sure that,
例如说，哦，我需要确保，
we have active replicas for all these rooms,
我们有活跃的复制对所有的房间，
that are that are on the other side of the partition,
它们位于分区的另一边，
wouldn't you have the same room hosts on both sides,
你不会在两边分区都有相同的房间，
No, because each room belongs only to like one worker,
不，因为每个房间只属于一个 worker ，
so like,
所以，比如，
so I guess, like each room, like can't,
所以我想，每个房间，比如不能，
like the replicas for the rooms would get abandoned,
比如房间的副本会被放弃，
so essentially what happens is,
所以从本质上讲，发生的是，
if a worker,
如果一个 worker ，
like in the case of a partition,
在分区的情况下，
the coordinator wouldn't be able to access a worker that's in the other partition,
coordinator 无法访问另一个分区中的 worker ，
so what happens is,
所以发生的事情是，
I think they like move their replicas over,
我觉得它们把副本移动，
but because the players also can't contact worker,
但因为玩家也不能联系 worker ，
none of the moves would be processed
所有移动都不会被处理，
and so the more recent replicas after the partition heals would be prioritized,
因此在分区修复之后，较新的副本将被优先处理，
when healing that network.
在修复那个网络的时候。
Why did you decide on that API with move
你为什么决定使用带有 Move 的 API
and sending a message.
以及发出一条信息？
So specifically for this API,
所以针对这个 API ，
we wanted two different types of moves,
我们想要两种不同类型的移动，
two distinct types of moves,
两种截然不同的移动，
demonstrate one, with a fast move, one with a stable move,
一个是快速移动，一个是稳定移动，
ideally stable move is used more like raraly
理想情况下，稳定移动使用很少，
and used more for transactions,
并更多地用于交易，
that where it's okay for it to take longer,
在那里花更长的时间是可以的，
but we wanted to not be dropped at all,
我们不想被丢弃，
the easiest way to replicate this in a simple frontend was with a chat message,
在一个简单的前端复制它的最简单的方法是通过聊天消息，
so it's kind of arbitrary,
所以这有点武断，
moves for sure should be fast,
移动当然应该是快的，
because we are, like we don't want it to be,
因为我们不想，
because players move a lot.
因为玩家经常移动。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Awesome, thanks so much,
太棒了，非常感谢，
that concludes the presentations,
演讲到此结束，
great job everyone,
大家都干得很好，
this was a pretty exciting.
这真是激动人心。
I have one more question for an old presentation, if that's possible.
我还有一个关于[]演示的问题，如果可能的话。
Yep, go ahead.
好的，继续。
So for the leader,
所以对于领导者来说，
I'm sorry, for distributed election system,
抱歉，对于分布式选举系统，
I'm not familiar lot with cryptography,
我对密码学不是很熟悉，
but I guess the system where you sum up all the results of the election
但我想系统对所有选举结果相加，
on a vote on a counter server,
在一个投票器服务器上，
this, wouldn't that [high] group attacks,
这个不是那个[]团队袭击，
for example if I have two servers,
例如，如果我有两台服务器，
and then I vote for different people on both servers,
然后我在两台服务器上投票给不同的人，
but then I coordinate with someone else
但之后我会和其他人协调，
to also vote in the other way around,
以另一种方式投票，
will eventually get the same vote factor,
最终将获得相同的投票因素，
but I would have thought it maliciously against,
但我会恶意地认为它反对，
I guess in this case wouldn't change the vote results,
我想这种情况下，不会改变投票结果，
or like the election result,
或者选举结果，
but I guess I would have acted incorrectly,
但我想我的行为是错误的，
so are there checks to make sure everybody voted correctly at each server.
所以，是否有检查以确保每个服务器上的每个人都正确投票。
Yeah.
是的。
Sorry, so we actually don't handle malicious voting,
抱歉，我们实际上不处理恶意投票，
which was which is which is pretty big,
这是一件很大的事情，
and you know I used to be pretty important for for real-world voting system,
对于现实世界的投票系统来说，非常重要，
but yeah I think like you know the scope of the project that we had
但是，我想我们的项目的范围，
and that we set out,
我们出发了，
it was just a little too complicated,
它有点太复杂了，
so we, yeah.
所以我们，是的。
I think we focus more on the distributed systems part,
我认为我们更关注分布式系统部分，
but if we wanted to provide more security,
但如果我们想提供更多的安全保障，
like for security,
比如为了安全，
using for example like an idea that we thought,
使用一个我们认为的想法，
but then decided to do,
但后来决定不这样做，
I was having a public ledger where you can make,
我有一个公共账本，
that they what you're posting like adds up
你发的帖子加起来，
and is what you're saying that it is
这就是你所说的，
and thinks of these things to handle malicious participants.
想到这些事情来处理恶意参与者。
Yeah.
好的。
So we're running a little bit late,
所以我们有点晚了，
yeah, it's in the class in principle
原则上，在课程中，
and anybody want to take around a question,
如果有人想提问，
feel free to stick around,
可以随意留下来，
as you want to say one of two things before closing since our last class meeting,
我想说一两件事，
first of all, I want to thank you for participating,
首先，我想感谢你们的参与，
even though it's another covid semester,
即使又是一个 covid 学期，
I feel I've interacted with many of you,
我觉得我已经和你们中的许多人互动过了，
you for email, we're indirectly
通过电子邮件，我们间接地，
and exchange lots of information
并交换大量的信息，
and I'd love to see you at some point in person,
我也很想在某个时候见到你本人，
actually know who you are,
真正知道你是谁，
the but, I appreciate all the participation.
但是，我很感谢大家的参与。
The second thing I want to thank TAs,
第二件事，是我想感谢助教，
it's an awesome set of TAs,
这是很棒的助教，
you probably realized, probably for many you,
你可能意识到，可能对很多人来说，
they figured out some bugs and helped you get through the labs
他们找出了一些 bug ，
and so I ran applause for the TAs,
所以我为助教们鼓掌，
very fortunate with this kind of quality.
非常幸运，有这样的品质。
And, I guess last thing I was to say,
我想我要说的最后一句话，
I guess good luck on the final
我想祝你在期末考试中好运，
and hopefully not too bad,
希望不会太糟，
and I hope you had learned something in 6.824
我希望你在 6.824 学到了一些东西，
and enjoyed it at the same time.
并同时享受它。
And anyone who wants to stick around,
任何想留下来的人，
please stick around,
请留下来，
you know more questions you want to ask to the different teams,
你想问不同团队更多的问题，
if the teams can stick around to be wonderful,
如果这团队还在，就很好，
otherwise, well, this is the end,
否则，这就结束了，
at least for the class meetings for 6.824.
至少 6.824 的课程。
Thank you all.
谢谢大家。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Thank you so much.
非常感谢。
Sorry, a quick question.
抱歉，我有个小问题。
Okay.
好的。
One last question now for real,
现在是最后一个问题了，
oh, I I oh I was wondering actually for for logistics for the exam,
哦，我在想考试的后勤，
I emailed you.
我给你发了电子邮件。
Yeah, yeah, we haven't gotten to the point, yet,
是的，我们还没到那个时间点，
we're dealing with the logistics of the example.
我们正在处理考试的后勤。
Okay.
好的。
A couple, aware of you two three [] to.
一对，两、三个。
We have plan, we haven't executed yet,
我们有计划，我们还没有执行，
noe shared any details.
不会分享任何细节。
Okay.
好的。
But it will happen.
但这是会发生的。
Sounds good.
听起来不错。
You don't need me to make sure you reach out.
你不需要我，确保在聊天中。
Alright, perfect,
好的，太好了，
thank you so much for everything,
非常感谢你所做的一切，
for the class and you know for the TAs.
对于班级和助教。
Thank you very much for all the class,
非常感谢你的所有课程，
so very fun I learned a lot.
非常有趣，我学到了很多。
Thank you, thank you for participating, asking all these questions,
谢谢你们，感谢你们的参与，
I appreciate it.
我很感激。
Yes, thank you,
好的，谢谢,
this is this is an awesome class,
这是一门很棒的课，
I really appreciate.
我真的很感激。
Things were being active during the class.
上课时一切都很活跃。
Okay, I guess that's probably,
好的，我想那可能是，
so I guess let's stop the recording.
所以我想我们停止录制。